<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2024-02-12T13:18:37+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">auditing TikTok</title><subtitle>our journey into TikTok&apos;s recommender systems
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">🛒 Ads, Ads, Ads</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/ads_ads_ads/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="🛒 Ads, Ads, Ads" /><published>2024-02-12T11:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-02-12T11:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/ads_ads_ads</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/ads_ads_ads/"><![CDATA[<p><em>By <a href="https://www.stiftung-nv.de/de/person/anna-semenova">Anna Semenova</a>, <a href="https://www.stiftung-nv.de/en/person/dr-martin-degeling">Martin Degeling</a> and <a href="https://www.stiftung-nv.de/en/person/dr-anna-katharina-messmer">Kathy Meßmer</a>.</em></p>

<p>Like other social media platforms, TikTok relies heavily on advertisements to sustain its operations. Marketing experts assessed that advertisers spent more than 3.8 billion US Dollar on TikTok in 2021, and <a href="https://www.insiderintelligence.com/content/tiktok-surpasses-snapchat-favorite-app-of-teens">forecasts expect these numbers to rise to 23 Billion in 2024</a>. The reasons for TikTok’s success are its young user base and the fact that advertising on the platform is as easy as posting a video. At the same time, many marketing techniques are available, including targeting users based on socio-demographic categories and interests.</p>

<p>As part of our <a href="https://tiktok-audit.com/blog/2024/TikTok-RSBA-Step1/">Risk Scenario-Based Audit</a> (RSBA) of TikTok, we have looked into TikTok’s advertising ecosystem. We discovered that up to one in three videos a user sees in their “For You”-feed contains paid advertising or direct brand mention. We also found that TikTok removes approximately 2.5% of the ads for violating their guidelines. Still, these removals are intransparent and can happen after thousands of users have already seen the ad.</p>

<p>Advertisers on TikTok have a <a href="https://insense.pro/blog/tiktok-ads">plethora of options</a> to get their message on the users’ display. The most common ones are “in-feed ads”, which are the main topic of this post. These video ads are seamlessly integrated into TikTok’s main feature, the video feed, allowing users to engage with them as they scroll through the “For You Page.”</p>

<p>TikTok’s advertising system leads to several challenges in consumer and youth protection. A report by the <a href="https://www.beuc.eu/sites/default/files/publications/beuc-x-2021-012_tiktok_without_filters.pdf">European Consumer Organisation (BEUC)</a> highlights instances where undisclosed or unlabeled content blurs the line between genuine engagement and commercial promotion. Moreover, we have previously shown that TikTok <a href="https://tiktok-audit.com/blog/2023/We-found-100-political-ads-on-TikTok-Germany/">fails to implement its own guidelines on political advertising</a> correctly, even within labeled ads.</p>

<style>
    video{max-height:500px}
</style>

<div class="row justify-content-sm-center"><div class="col-sm-6 mt-6 mt-md-6">


<figure>

  

  <video muted="" controls="" autoplay="" preload="auto">
    <source src="/assets/video/2024-02_TikTok-AdCount.webm" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="50%" height="auto" type="video/webm" />
  </video>

  

</figure>
 
</div></div>

<h2 id="definitions">Definitions</h2>

<p>To facilitate our analysis, we classify TikTok advertising into two categories:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Paid promotion:</strong> Content published and paid for, e.g., by a brand or company, via official TikTok advertising tools. It is discernible as an advertisement on TikTok. Paid content is also where TikTok takes its share. Paid content can appear in the For You feed as well as on other features like search results.</li>
  <li><strong>Organic/Influencer marketing</strong>: Content that targets an audience through the viral effects of the platform rather than relying on paid promotion. This marketing approach is closely linked with influencer marketing, wherein users receive compensation to promote a product or service, leveraging the authenticity of these influencers for the benefit of the brand. When publishing their content, creators are asked to disclose if the video promotes something. If they choose to disclose this, the video will also be labeled as “Anzeige” (“Paid Partnership” in English).
    <ol>
      <li><em>Cooperation:</em> Influencers with large audiences often rely on agencies to manage brand partnerships. However, TikTok also provides its <a href="https://creatormarketplace.tiktok.com/">“Creator Marketplace”</a> (a service for which it takes a share) to facilitate cooperation. Creators can label these videos as ads during the publishing process and may include “Ad” in the video description.</li>
      <li><em>Self-Marketing:</em> Users can also advertise their own products or services. TikTok is known for being a place where <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/10/02/style/tiktok-shopping-viral-products.html">products go viral</a>, and people try their luck with dropshipping online shops or affiliate marketing. When advertising their products, they are also asked to disclose this advertisement to be labeled as ads.</li>
      <li><em>Unpaid Consumer to Consumer Marketing</em><strong>:</strong> The last category of organic marketing involves consumers advertising products to other consumers. Often, these videos are variations of the Haul, in which users disclose product details, prices, and sources without receiving payment from the brands they review.</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>The boundaries between different types of advertising are blurry. For instance, a video that has been created through cooperation between an influencer and a brand may also be promoted via paid promotion to reach a larger audience (with the hope of “going viral” after the initial forced push). Additionally, as we have described in the case of <a href="https://www.notion.so/2024-01-10-Shop-Till-You-Drop-How-Temu-s-exploitation-of-TikTok-affordances-creates-an-abyss-of--2243d97825cc423fae6aa350e30b2fe9?pvs=21">Temu</a>, companies try to nudge users into creating videos that end up being unpaid consumer to consumer marketing when users are offered a discount on their <em>next</em> purchase.</p>

<center>
<figure class="justify-content-sm-center">

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2024-02_tt_ad_label_example-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2024-02_tt_ad_label_example-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2024-02_tt_ad_label_example-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/2024-02_tt_ad_label_example.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture><figcaption class="caption">Example of an advertising label on TikTok in Germany. 'Anzeige' is German for 'Advertising'. On the English app version, the videos are labeled as 'Sponsored.'</figcaption>

</figure>
</center>

<p>Formally, only the first one (”paid promotion”) falls under the definition of advertisement according to the Digital Services Act (DSA): “<em>‘advertisement’ means information designed to promote the message of a legal or natural person, irrespective of whether to achieve commercial or non-commercial purposes and presented by an online platform on its online interface against remuneration specifically for promoting that information</em>” (DSA, Art. 3 (r)). Thus, TikTok as a platform has to be involved in the monetary flow.</p>

<p>Moreover, this type of advertising should be accessible on the TikTok <a href="https://library.tiktok.com/">Ad Library</a>, a repository mandated by the DSA for very large online platforms platforms. The DSA specifies that VLOPs must ensure public access to repositories of advertisements presented on their online interfaces, facilitating supervision and research into emerging risks associated with online advertising (Recital 95).</p>

<h2 id="methodology">Methodology</h2>

<p>For our analysis, we concentrated on the in-feed ads, particularly emphasizing paid promotions. To gather quantitative data for a more comprehensive analysis, we conducted a (semi-)automated audit of 39 accounts based on different personas (for which we had defined, e.g., age, gender and interests like “fashion” or “finance”). After we had manually trained these accounts and collected the training data, they were automated to continue the data collection. The automated data collection involved swiping through the For You feed for about 20 minutes a day while intercepting network traffic and storing metadata on videos, comments, ads, and more. In the coming weeks, we will publish a more in-depth description of our methodology. All tests were conducted using IP addresses implying that the user resides in Germany.</p>

<h2 id="every-fifth-video-in-the-for-you-feed-is-paid-promotion">Every fifth video in the For You feed is paid promotion</h2>

<p>Our dataset sheds light on a significant prevalence of advertisements on TikTok. Of the 94,854 videos in our database (as of Jan 27th, 2024), 14,523, or 15.3%, were shown as paid promotions in our users’ feeds. However, this is just a comparison at the level of unique videos. While regular videos are mostly shown once, ads can target multiple users in a target group multiple times. For example, this <a href="https://library.tiktok.com/ads/detail/?ad_id=1784736476404737">ad for Disney+</a> was shown to 9 million users in Germany. In our sample, the ad appeared on 13 of 39 accounts and 5 accounts even saw it twice. At the same time, only a handful of non-ad videos came across the For You feeds of different accounts in our sample.</p>

<p>The plot below shows the share of ads per day during our automated data collection phase. Looking at the total share of ads per user, the average in January was around 19.9% - that is 1 in 5 videos.</p>

<script type="text/javascript">window.PlotlyConfig = {MathJaxConfig: 'local'};</script>

<script src="/assets/js/plotly.js" type="text/javascript"></script>

<center><div id="9971be77-cf72-4de2-a3d7-fd10bbb72ad1" class="plotly-graph-div" style="width:770px"></div></center>
<script src="/assets/plotly/2024-02_ad_share.js"></script>
<figcaption class="caption">Each line represents a user from our training sample. The share of ads is characterized by variability, with noticeable fluctuations for individual users from one day to the next. The black dashed line represents the average per day.</figcaption>

<p>Importantly, this figure exclusively pertains to the count of paid promotion content. However, learning more about the organic marketing part of the platform is much more complicated. As explained above, creators are asked when uploading videos whether the content is advertising something. But only 0.8% of videos in our dataset were labeled as “Promotional Content” or “Paid Partnership” by the creators. If you have ever used TikTok, you might have noticed that this is a surprisingly low number in itself. But interestingly enough, that also means that even videos that are uploaded for paid promotion via TikTok are not labeled as “Promotional Content” by the uploading creators.</p>

<p>For us, as third-party auditors, researching TikTok from the outside, it is hard to tell if a video creator received money from a company. We found a small number of 179 videos, which is 0.1% of our sample, that used a specific hashtag like #ad (or #anzeige in German) or clearly named the fact of being paid in the description of the video, while at the same time, they were not visibly labeled as “paid partnership”.</p>

<h2 id="some-brands-rely-on-unpaid-advertisements-on-tiktok">Some brands rely on unpaid advertisements on TikTok</h2>

<p>However, organic marketing drives the ad ratio higher than 20%. To give you an example: We trained four accounts on fashion interests. Of the 8964 videos those four accounts saw, 11% mentioned specific brands. The short list of fashion brands we noticed included Action, Primark, Shein, Sheglam, Temu and Zara. Of those, all but Zara completely rely on “organic” unpaid advertisements. Only <a href="https://library.tiktok.com/ads?region=DE&amp;start_time=1701385200000&amp;end_time=1706569200000&amp;adv_name=ZARA%20ESPA%C3%91A%20SA&amp;adv_biz_ids=6952877848373756673&amp;query_type=2&amp;sort_type=last_shown_date,desc">Zara</a> can easily be found in the ad library, with a handful of ads during the test period. We recently highlighted the problems with this form of advertising using the example of <a href="https://tiktok-audit.com/blog/2024/temu-tiktok/">Temu</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Combined with the paid promtions, for the accounts trained in fashion, roughly one of three videos is an ad.</strong></p>

<p>This analysis has some significant limitations as it is based on hashtags, which were only available for around 70% of the videos in this dataset.</p>

<h2 id="most-paid-promotion-ads-target-small-audiences">Most paid promotion ads target small audiences</h2>

<script type="text/javascript">window.PlotlyConfig = {MathJaxConfig: 'local'};</script>

<script src="/assets/js/plotly.js" type="text/javascript"></script>

<center><div id="ceba7163-8f49-4dcc-9e4f-c44ef053c008" class="plotly-graph-div" style="width:770px"></div></center>
<script src="/assets/plotly/2024-02_ad_cummulative.js"></script>
<figcaption class="caption">The chart illustrates the cumulative distribution of advertisements based on the share of users they are exposed to. The x-axis, 'Share of Users,' indicates the proportion of users to whom an ad is shown, while the y-axis, 'Cumulative Frequency (%),' represents the cumulative percentage of ads falling within or below each share-of-users category.</figcaption>

<p>The chart above shows that a significant portion of videos, accounting for over 60% of all ads, is exclusively shown to a single user within our group of test accounts. Approximately 80% of ads are presented to a maximum of two users, implying that <strong>only around 20% of ads extend their reach to more than two users in our test group</strong>. The distribution shows that the Disney+ ad mentioned above is an outlier. This is likely an effect of limited ad spending on the majority of campaigns that limit their reach to a small audience. This leads to a high number of ads, but a limited number of ad campaigns reaching a large audience on TikTok.</p>

<h1 id="insights-from-the-ad-library">Insights from the ad library</h1>

<p>TikTok’s <a href="https://library.tiktok.com/">ad library</a> should give simple access and allow the exploration of ads. The repository provides insights into the general statistics on “paid promotion” ads. For example, during our data analysis period, which spanned from November 28, 2023, to January 27, 2024, <strong>1,861,925 ads targeting Germany were recorded in the repository</strong>.</p>

<h2 id="18-million-ads-in-the-last-two-months">1.8 million ads in the last two months</h2>

<p>However, besides these general statistics, the ad library could be more usable as the search is more or less dysfunctional, and it is often impossible to find information about an ad you saw in your feed.</p>

<p>Therefore, we developed our own means of access to be able to match the paid content shown to our sock puppets with the ads in the library. We found that over 1.8 million ads targeted users in Germany over the last two months; on average, each ad campaign had a duration of just 2 days, calculated as the difference between the first and last display date. During that time, the typical ad garnered around 1000 impressions, as indicated by the median value. This means that more then half of the ads received fewer than 1000 impressions or fewer, see figure below.</p>

<script type="text/javascript">window.PlotlyConfig = {MathJaxConfig: 'local'};</script>

<script src="/assets/js/plotly.js" type="text/javascript"></script>

<center><div id="82c56e4d-af1d-48dd-ba67-9c0629b54050" class="plotly-graph-div" style="width:770px"></div></center>
<script src="/assets/plotly/2024-02_ad_impressions.js"></script>
<figcaption class="caption">The plot shows the number of <b>published</b> (upper chart) <b>removed</b> (lower chart) ads listed by the number of impressions in Germany confirming the outlier position of the Disney+ ad, which falls in the highest category of 10-20 million impressions.</figcaption>

<h2 id="removing-ads-is-slow-and-usually-happens-after-ads-have-reached-their-audience">Removing ads is slow and usually happens after ads have reached their audience</h2>

<p>While the ad library has some volatility, making it hard to get exact numbers, we found 50,279 (2.7%) ads being removed in Germany during our two month test period, citing reasons such as the expiration of authorization or violations of the terms of service. Interestingly, the average campaign duration of removed ads was also two days, meaning those ads still reached their audience before removal. 129 ads even reached more than 1 million users before they were removed. <strong>Unfortunately, TikTok deletes any identifying information from ads when they are removed from the ad library</strong>, so it is impossible to know what these ads had shown.</p>

<p>However, even if an ad is removed, the video can still be available on TikTok as non-ad content - it is just not promoted as ad anymore. In our dataset, we caught 20 ads that were removed after they had been viewed by our accounts, and since the videos were still available, we were able to review which ads were deleted. Here are a two examples:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.tiktok.com/@FocusUp/video/7325217813247921409">This entirely AI-generated video</a> promoting Ashwagandha tea is still online as content but was <a href="https://library.tiktok.com/ads/detail/?ad_id=1788382923589681">removed</a> as ad after running for five days and being shown to 3000 users. TikTok gives the following reasons for removing it as an ad: “The product/service promoted on the ad/landing page belongs to a prohibited industry of the targeted location(s)[…]”</li>
  <li>This <a href="https://www.tiktok.com/@credimaxx/video/7252671337053850885">ad</a>, removed for making an “exaggerated financial claim” (it says that “even with a negative credit rating you would have <em>an excellent chance</em> to get a credit between 500 and 35.000€), was <a href="https://library.tiktok.com/ads/detail/?ad_id=1770675512982530">shown to 281.000 users</a> over six(!) months before it was removed as an ad.</li>
</ul>

<p>Finding these examples took effort, and TikTok is not making it easy to understand which ads are removed and why. The ad library is mostly a transparency theatre, and we’ll publish more on that in one of the next posts.</p>

<h2 id="limitations">Limitations</h2>

<p>As noted above, our methodology has some limitations:</p>

<ul>
  <li>We gathered data on the For You feed in Germany and for specific personas. This does not reflect the general audience. Therefore, we additionally collected data in a user survey that we will publish later. We also cross checked our data with other sources, and our observation of roughly 20% paid promotional content was confirmed in this <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/tiktokgossip/comments/14cyhqz/im_seriously_getting_an_ad_every_4_vids_on_tiktok/">reddit thread</a>.</li>
  <li>There was an issue with our data collection over the Christmas holidays, making it impossible to assign videos watched to the persona between the end of manual training and December 27th. This affected 22 accounts. We, therefore, limited the analysis relying on the persona to data collected after December 27th.</li>
  <li>As mentioned above, finding ads in the “grey area” where the creator is seeking financial gain from reviewing or showcasing a product is difficult. We, therefore, chose very specific criteria (using the hashtag #ad or #anzeige or mentioning the brand) to get a lower bound for this type of consumer-to-consumer marketing. Future research should try to narrow down features to identify this type of marketing, similar to TikTok trying to leverage this by <a href="https://gizmodo.com/tiktok-testing-users-will-put-up-every-video-being-ad-1851207082">automatically identifying products and advertising their own shop</a>.</li>
  <li>We also noted that the ad library is rather volatile and changes are made after ads have been published. We continuously scraped the library from November 2023 on for new ads published at least 48 hours ago, but also going back to September 2023. We only checked again for ads we encountered with our automated accounts to fill gaps in our dataset; we do not have a complete mirror of it.</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Anna Semenova, Martin Degeling and Kathy Meßmer</name></author><category term="rsba," /><category term="ad-library" /><category term="ads," /><category term="marketing," /><category term="fyp" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How the for you feed is clogged with ads.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">⚖️ What the first months of DSA enforcement have meant for TikTok</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/DSA-TikTok/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="⚖️ What the first months of DSA enforcement have meant for TikTok" /><published>2024-02-09T09:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-02-09T09:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/DSA-TikTok</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/DSA-TikTok/"><![CDATA[<p><em>By <a href="https://www.stiftung-nv.de/de/person/dr-julian-jaursch">Julian Jaursch</a></em></p>

<p>The EU’s major new platform regulation law, the Digital Services Act (DSA), requires online platforms to explain their recommender systems, have user-friendly reporting mechanisms for potentially illegal content, label advertising and report on how they try to ensure diligent and non-arbitrary content moderation. Bigger platforms such as TikTok have to fulfill additional obligations such as conducting risk assessments.</p>

<p>While the DSA only takes/took full effect in mid-February 2024, rules for such “very large online platforms” (VLOPs) – those with more than 45 million users in the EU per month – have been in place since the summer of 2023. What have the first months of enforcement brought for TikTok?</p>

<h1 id="compliance-assurances"><strong>Compliance (assurances)</strong></h1>

<p>TikTok was adamant about fulfilling the DSA’s obligations ahead of the legal deadline. In a <a href="https://newsroom.tiktok.com/en-eu/fulfilling-commitments-dsa-update">blog post</a> in early August 2023, the company said it had introduced an additional reporting mechanism for users and expanded on the explanations of content moderation and recommender systems, among other things. It also <a href="https://www.tiktok.com/business/en/blog/privacy-updates-improved-data-control-transparency-tools">stated</a> it would not show personalized ads to minors. <a href="https://tiktok-audit.com/blog/2023/Minors-a-la-carte-TikTok-allows-profiling-of-underage-teens/">Research by my colleagues</a> posted on this blog cast some doubt on this.</p>

<p>The fact that TikTok tries to comply with the DSA and makes public announcements on product or policy changes related to the new rules is a promising sign that the DSA is working: It puts some pressure even on bigger platforms to make changes. The <a href="https://newsroom.tiktok.com/en-eu/expanding-tiktoks-research-api-and-commercial-content-library">expansion</a> of the researcher API from the US to Europe can also be viewed in this context. The API is not fully meeting researchers’ expectations yet, as this blog has documented early on. At least <a href="https://digitalmonitor.democracy-reporting.org/data-access/">compared to other services</a>, though, there are steps in the right direction.</p>

<p>All of this is not to say that the early months of DSA enforcement have been rosy for TikTok.</p>

<h1 id="commission-requests-for-information"><strong>Commission requests for information</strong></h1>

<p>The European Commission oversees VLOPs’ compliance with the DSA and has kept an eye on TikTok and other companies. In late 2023, it sent <a href="https://digital-strategy.ec.europa.eu/en/policies/list-designated-vlops-and-vloses">formal requests for information</a> to various VLOPs on different topics (see table below). This can be the first step towards formal investigations under the DSA but does not have to be. The requests are mostly based on the internal risk assessments that VLOPs provided to the Commission in August 2023. If the Commission saw open questions, they sent the requests to the companies.</p>

<iframe src="https://flo.uri.sh/visualisation/16732340/embed" title="Interactive or visual content" class="flourish-embed-iframe" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" style="width:100%;height:800px;" sandbox="allow-same-origin allow-forms allow-scripts allow-downloads allow-popups allow-popups-to-escape-sandbox allow-top-navigation-by-user-activation"></iframe>
<div style="width:100%!;margin-top:4px!important;text-align:right!important;"><a class="flourish-credit" href="https://public.flourish.studio/visualisation/16732340/?utm_source=embed&amp;utm_campaign=visualisation/16732340" target="_top" style="text-decoration:none!important"><img alt="Made with Flourish" src="https://public.flourish.studio/resources/made_with_flourish.svg" style="width:105px!important;height:16px!important;border:none!important;margin:0!important;" /> </a></div>

<p>It is difficult to judge the platforms’ or the Commission’s job because the risk assessments are not public. What did the platforms write about? What did the Commission miss? To answer such questions, researchers, journalists and users have to wait until summaries of risk assessments come out, which will be only after the VLOPs have been audited by external auditors.</p>

<p>From <a href="https://digital-strategy.ec.europa.eu/en/policies/list-designated-vlops-and-vloses#ecl-inpage-tiktok">TikTok</a>, the Commission wanted to know how the company follows the rules on</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://digital-strategy.ec.europa.eu/en/news/commission-sends-request-information-tiktok-under-digital-services-act">Risk “mitigation measures</a> against the spreading of illegal content, in particular the spreading of terrorist and violent content and hate speech, as well as the alleged spread of disinformation”</li>
  <li><a href="https://digital-strategy.ec.europa.eu/en/news/commission-sends-requests-information-tiktok-and-youtube-under-digital-services-act">Protection</a> of minors generally and the risk assessments regarding risks for minors in particular, with an emphasis on risks to mental health and physical health</li>
  <li><a href="https://digital-strategy.ec.europa.eu/en/news/commission-sends-requests-information-17-very-large-online-platforms-and-search-engines-under">Providing</a> access to publicly available data</li>
</ul>

<p>Whatever the metrics might be, this shows the Commission was not satisfied with the quantitative and/or qualitative data it received in TikTok’s risk assessment. Yet, at least the risk assessment was filed and the communication between regulator and company works. With the DSA in its early enforcement stages, this is the minimum of what needs to happen. It would have been surprising if everything at TikTok – from recommender system transparency to content moderation reporting to risk assessments – had fallen into place immediately and the Commission had not had any questions. It seems as if TikTok (and other companies) are already doing their DSA homework, but some improvements might still be necessary. With every iteration of the risk assessment cycle, the Commission and especially external observers should demand and check on these improvements.</p>

<p>Some outside checks on TikTok and other VLOPs are important particularly because companies will seek ways to get out of DSA obligations.</p>

<h1 id="lawsuit-against-the-commission"><strong>Lawsuit against the Commission</strong></h1>

<p>TikTok filed a <a href="https://www.politico.eu/article/tiktok-joins-meta-in-suing-eu-over-online-content-rulebook/">lawsuit against the Commission</a>, albeit not one on substantive DSA due diligence obligations. The company argues that the fees tied to its designation as a VLOP are calculated unfairly. TikTok and Meta, which also sued the Commission over this, are not happy that they have to pay millions in supervisory fees per year, while platforms with smaller or no profits contribute nothing. The fee is important to help finance the Commission’s platform oversight structure.</p>

<p>The Commission claims its <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/en/TXT/?uri=CELEX:32023R1127">methodology</a> for calculating the fee is just fine and now it will be up to the EU’s General Court to decide whether that is the case. It is not known how much TikTok is supposed to pay (Meta said its payment obligation for 2024 was 11 million euros; the company had a <a href="https://investor.fb.com/investor-news/press-release-details/2024/Meta-Reports-Fourth-Quarter-and-Full-Year-2023-Results-Initiates-Quarterly-Dividend/default.aspx">net income 14 billion US dollars</a> in the last three months of 2023).</p>

<p>Considering the compliance successes and struggles, the information requests and the lawsuit together offers a murky picture of early DSA enforcement: Key questions around the law are open or will be challenged in court over the next couple of years. Apart from companies, regulators and courts, it will be up to media, civil society and researchers to center users’ rights throughout these processes.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="DSA" /><category term="analysis" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[(and other big platforms)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">🛫 Auditing TikTok: Methodological reflections on the RSBA process</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/TikTok-RSBA-Step1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="🛫 Auditing TikTok: Methodological reflections on the RSBA process" /><published>2024-01-19T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-01-19T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/TikTok-RSBA-Step1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/TikTok-RSBA-Step1/"><![CDATA[<p><em>By <a href="https://www.stiftung-nv.de/en/person/dr-anna-katharina-messmer">Kathy Meßmer</a>, <a href="https://www.stiftung-nv.de/en/person/dr-martin-degeling">Martin Degeling</a>, <a href="https://www.stiftung-nv.de/en/person/alexander-hohlfeld">Alexander Hohlfeld</a>.</em></p>

<p>In February 2023, we published a framework for “<a href="https://www.stiftung-nv.de/de/publication/auditing-recommender-systems">Auditing Recommender Systems</a>”. With reference to the Digital Services Act (DSA), we have outlined how risk assessments and algorithm audits of recommender systems of very large online platforms (VLOPs) should be conducted. Therefore, we proposed a risk-scenario-based audit process (RSBA).</p>

<p>But we didn’t just want to theorize; we also wanted to walk the talk and test our approach by auditing TikTok <a href="https://ec.europa.eu/commission/presscorner/detail/en/IP_23_2413">(which is designated as a VLOP under the DSA</a>). <strong>Over the upcoming weeks, we will publish our findings here on the blog.</strong></p>

<p>Before we do so, let us give you an overview of our findings and methodological decisions generated throughout Step 1 of the RSBA process.</p>

<p>As a quick recap, the RSBA process comprises the following 4 steps:</p>

<div class="row" style="width:100%; margin-bottom:1em">
<style>
    /* Temporary styles for development */

@font-face {
    font-family: 'Akkurat-Regular';
    src: url('/assets/fonts/AkkuratStd-Regular.woff2') format('woff2'),
        url('/assets/fonts/AkkuratStd-Regular.woff') format('woff');
    font-weight: normal;
    font-style: normal;
    font-display: swap;
}

@font-face {
    font-family: 'Akkurat-Regular';
    src: url('fonts/AkkuratStd-Bold.woff2') format('woff2'),
        url('fonts/AkkuratStd-Bold.woff') format('woff');
    font-weight: bold;
    font-style: normal;
    font-display: swap;
}

html {
    font-family: 'Akkurat-Regular', Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif;
}

body {
    display: flex;
    min-height: 100vh;
    flex-direction: column;
    justify-content: center;
    align-items: center;
    max-width: 690px;
    margin: 0 auto;
}

#snv-graphic-container {
    width: 100%;
    font-family: 'Akkurat-Regular', Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif;
    min-height: 500px;
    position: relative;
}

/* Definitive styles for realisation */

/* Variables */
:root {
    --snv-graphic-orange: #ff8c14;
    --snv-graphic-orange-light: #fae1a5;
    --snv-graphic-pink: #f02878;
    --snv-graphic-pink-light: #ef78ae;
    --snv-graphic-blue: #b914ff;
    --snv-graphic-blue-light: #d197ff;
    --snv-graphic-yellow: #ffc850;
    --snv-graphic-yellow-light: #fff6a6;
    --snv-graphic-green: #00c43c;
    --snv-graphic-grey: #6e7682;
}

/* Buttons */
.snv-graphic-btn > button {
    background-color: white;
}

.snv-graphic-btn > button:hover,
.snv-graphic-submenu > button:hover{
    cursor: pointer;
}

.snv-graphic-btn-orange-light > button {
    border: 1px solid var(--snv-graphic-orange-light);
}

.snv-graphic-btn-pink-light > button {
    border: 1px solid var(--snv-graphic-pink-light);
}

.snv-graphic-btn-blue-light > button{
    border: 1px solid var(--snv-graphic-blue-light);
}

.snv-graphic-btn-yellow-light > button {
    border: 1px solid var(--snv-graphic-yellow-light);
}

.snv-graphic-btn-orange > button {
    border: 1px solid var(--snv-graphic-orange);
}

.snv-graphic-btn-pink > button {
    border: 1px solid var(--snv-graphic-pink);
}

.snv-graphic-btn-blue > button {
    border: 1px solid var(--snv-graphic-blue);
}

.snv-graphic-btn-yellow > button {
    border: 1px solid var(--snv-graphic-yellow);
}

.snv-graphic-btn-orange-light:hover > button,
.snv-graphic-btn-orange-light .btn-active  {
    background-color: var(--snv-graphic-orange-light);
}

.snv-graphic-btn-pink-light:hover > button,
.snv-graphic-btn-pink-light .btn-active  {
    background-color: var(--snv-graphic-pink-light);
}


.snv-graphic-btn-blue-light:hover > button,
.snv-graphic-btn-blue-light .btn-active  {
    background-color: var(--snv-graphic-blue-light);
}

.snv-graphic-btn-yellow-light:hover > button,
.snv-graphic-btn-yellow-light .btn-active  {
    background-color: var(--snv-graphic-yellow-light);
}


.snv-graphic-icon-btn {
    display: flex;
    flex-direction: row;
    align-items: center;
    justify-content: center;
    gap: 10px;
}

.snv-graphic-icon-btn > svg {
    width: 20px;
    height: 20px;
}

/* Select */
#snv-graphic-container select,
#snv-graphic-container button {
    font-family: 'Akkurat-Regular', Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif;
}

#snv-graphic-container select:focus {
    outline: none;
}

/* Header */
#snv-graphic-header {
    position: absolute;
    display: flex;
    flex-wrap: wrap;
    flex-direction: row;
    gap: 16px;
    width: 100%;
}

#snv-graphic-header > .snv-graphic-button-wrapper {
    width: calc( (100% - 16px) / 2 );
}

#snv-graphic-header button {
    font-family: 'Akkurat-Regular', Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif;
    border-radius: 5px;
    width: 100%;
}

#snv-graphic-main button {
    font-family: 'Akkurat-Regular', Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif;
}

.header-max button {
    height: 60px;
    font-size: 20px;
    transition: 0.4s ease;
}

.header-min button {
    height: 40px;
    font-size: 14px;
    transition: 0.4s ease;
}

.header-max {
    top: 50%;
    transform: translateY(-40%);
}

.header-min {
    top: 0;
    transform: normal;
    transition: 0.4s ease;
}

.snv-graphic-button-info {
    width: 100%;
    text-align: center;
    font-size: 12px;
    opacity: 0;
    transition: 0.2s ease;
    padding-top: 16px;
    display: none;
}

.header-max > .snv-graphic-button-wrapper:hover .snv-graphic-button-info {
    opacity: 1;
    transition: 0.2s ease;
}

.header-min .snv-graphic-button-info {
    display: none;
}

/* Start item */
.snv-graphic-start-item {
    background-color: white;
    position: relative;
    width: 100%;
    height: 50px;
    font-size: 16px;
    border-radius: 5px;
    border: 1px dashed var(--snv-graphic-orange-light); 
    position: absolute;
    text-align: center;
    transition: 0.4s ease;
}

.snv-graphic-start-item:hover {
    background-color: var(--snv-graphic-orange-light);
    transition: 0.4s ease;
}

.snv-graphic-start-item .snv-graphic-arrow {
    opacity: 0;
    transition: 0.4s ease;
}

.snv-graphic-start-item:hover .snv-graphic-arrow {
    opacity: 1;
    transition: 0.4s ease;
}

.item-top {
    top: 0;
}

.item-bottom {
    bottom: 0;
}

.snv-graphic-arrow {
    position: absolute;
    left: 50%;
    transform: translateX(-50%);
    height: 60px;
    width: 1px;
    background-color: black;
}

.arrow-down {
    top: 70px;
}

.snv-graphic-arrow span {
    border-top: 10px solid black;
    border-left: 8px solid transparent;
    border-right: 8px solid transparent;
    position: absolute;
    bottom: 0;
    left: 50%;
    transform: translateX(-50%);
}

.arrow-up {
    bottom: 70px;
}

/* Main */
#snv-graphic-main {
    width: 100%;
    padding-top: 96px;
}

.main-hide {
    transform: translateY(300px);
    opacity: 0;
    transition: 0.4s ease;
}

.main-show {
    transform: normal;
    opacity: 1;
    transition: 0.4s ease;
}

.snv-graphic-layer {
    width: 100%;
    padding-top: 16px;
}

.snv-graphic-sidebar {
    width: 100%;
}

.snv-graphic-sidebar p,
.snv-graphic-sidebar a {
    margin-top: 0px;
    font-size: 12px;
    line-height: 1.5;
}

.layer-hide {
    display: none;
}

.layer-show {
    display: block;
}

.snv-graphic-main-container {
    width: 100%;
    display: flex;
    flex-direction: column;
    gap: 16px;
    padding-top: 32px;
}

.snv-graphic-layer select {
    width: 100%;
    padding: 4px 8px;
    font-size: 12px;
    border-radius: 5px;
    background-color: white;
}

.snv-graphic-layer select > option {
    background-color: white;
}

#snv-graphic-plan select {
    border: 1px solid var(--snv-graphic-orange-light);
}

#snv-graphic-scenarios select {
    border: 1px solid var(--snv-graphic-pink-light);
}

#snv-graphic-measure select {
    border: 1px solid var(--snv-graphic-blue-light);
}

#snv-graphic-measure select.measure-audit {
    border: 1px solid var(--snv-graphic-blue);
}

#snv-graphic-measure select.measure-element {
    border: 1px solid var(--snv-graphic-orange);
}

#snv-graphic-evaluate select {
    border: 1px solid var(--snv-graphic-yellow-light);
}

#snv-graphic-plan select:hover,
#snv-graphic-measure select.measure-element:hover {
    background-color: var(--snv-graphic-orange-light);
}

#snv-graphic-scenarios select:hover {
    background-color: var(--snv-graphic-pink-light);
}

#snv-graphic-measure select:hover,
#snv-graphic-measure select.measure-audit:hover {
    background-color: var(--snv-graphic-blue-light);
}

#snv-graphic-evaluate select:hover {
    background-color: var(--snv-graphic-yellow-light);
}

.snv-graphic-content {
    width: 100%;
}

/* Graphic elements */
.snv-graphic-element-btn {
    fill: white;
}

.snv-graphic-element-text {
    opacity: 0;
    transition: 0.2s ease;
}

.snv-graphic-element:hover .snv-graphic-element-text {
    opacity: 1;
    transition: 0.2s ease;
}

.snv-graphic-element-orange {
    stroke: var(--snv-graphic-orange);
    fill: white;
}

.snv-graphic-element:hover .snv-graphic-element-orange,
.snv-graphic-element-orange:hover {
    fill: var(--snv-graphic-orange-light);
}

.snv-graphic-element-pink {
    stroke: var(--snv-graphic-pink);
    fill: white;
}

.snv-graphic-element:hover .snv-graphic-element-pink,
.snv-graphic-element-pink:hover {
    fill: var(--snv-graphic-pink-light);
}

.snv-graphic-element-blue {
    stroke: var(--snv-graphic-blue);
    fill: white;
}

.snv-graphic-element:hover .snv-graphic-element-blue,
.snv-graphic-element-blue:hover {
    fill: var(--snv-graphic-blue-light);
}

.snv-graphic-element-yellow {
    stroke: var(--snv-graphic-yellow);
    fill: white;
}

.snv-graphic-element:hover .snv-graphic-element-yellow,
.snv-graphic-element-yellow:hover {
    fill: var(--snv-graphic-yellow-light);
}

#snv-graphic-scenarios-define #scenarios-define-01 {
    opacity: 1;
    transition: 0.4s ease;
} 

#snv-graphic-scenarios-define #scenarios-define-02 {
    opacity: 0;
    transition: 0.4s ease;
} 

#snv-graphic-scenarios-define:hover #scenarios-define-02 {
    opacity: 1;
    transition: 0.4s ease;
} 

#snv-graphic-scenarios-define:hover #scenarios-define-01 {
    opacity: 0;
    transition: 0.4s ease;
} 

.snv-graphic-measure-prioritize-text,
.snv-graphic-measure-prioritize-element {
    opacity: 0;
    transition: 0.4s ease;
}

.snv-graphic-measure-prioritize-container:hover .snv-graphic-measure-prioritize-text,
.snv-graphic-measure-prioritize-container:hover .snv-graphic-measure-prioritize-element {
    opacity: 1;
    transition: 0.4s ease;
}

.snv-graphic-measure-prioritize-container:hover .snv-graphic-element-pink {
    fill: var(--snv-graphic-pink-light);
}

.snv-graphic-measure-prioritize-container:hover .snv-graphic-element-yellow {
    fill: var(--snv-graphic-yellow-light);
}

#snv-graphic-measure-audits {
    width: 100%;
}

#snv-graphic-measure-audits-header > p {
    margin-top: 0;
    margin-bottom: 10px;
    font-weight: bold;
    font-size: 14px;
}

#snv-graphic-measure-audits-body > p {
    margin-bottom: 10px;
    font-size: 14px;
    margin-top: 20px;
}

#snv-graphic-measure-audits-header,
#snv-graphic-measure-audits-body {
    display: flex;
    flex-direction: column;
    align-items: center;
}

#snv-graphic-measure-audits-header > select,
#snv-graphic-measure-audits-body .snv-graphic-measure-button {
    width: 200px;
    height: 40px;
    font-size: 12px;
    border-radius: 5px;
}

.snv-graphic-measure-element {
    margin-bottom: 8px;
}

.snv-graphic-measure-button {
    display: flex;
    align-items: center;
    justify-content: center;
}

.measure-audit {
    border: 1px solid var(--snv-graphic-blue);
}

.measure-audit:hover {
    background-color: var(--snv-graphic-blue-light);
}

.measure-element {
    border: 1px solid var(--snv-graphic-orange);
}

.measure-element:hover {
    background-color: var(--snv-graphic-orange-light);
}

.snv-graphic-measure-text {
    width: 176px;
    padding: 8px;
    border: 1px solid black;
    opacity: 0;
    text-align: center;
    margin-top: 5px;
    font-size: 12px;
    transition: 0.4s ease;
    position: absolute;
    bottom: 0;
}

.snv-graphic-measure-element:hover > .snv-graphic-measure-text {
    opacity: 1;
    transition: 0.4s ease;
}

/* Submenu */
.snv-submenu-button {
    border-radius: 5px;
    height: 28px;
    width: calc( (100% - 16px) / 2 );
}

.snv-graphic-submenu {
    width: 100%;
    display: flex;
    justify-content: center;
    gap: 16px;
}

#snv-graphic-plan .snv-submenu-button {
    background-color: white;
    border: 1px solid var(--snv-graphic-orange-light);
}

#snv-graphic-plan .snv-submenu-button:hover,
#snv-graphic-plan .btn-active {
    background-color: var(--snv-graphic-orange-light);
}

#snv-graphic-scenarios .snv-submenu-button {
    background-color: white;
    border: 1px solid var(--snv-graphic-pink-light);
}

#snv-graphic-scenarios .snv-submenu-button:hover,
#snv-graphic-scenarios .btn-active {
    background-color: var(--snv-graphic-pink-light);
}

#snv-graphic-measure .snv-submenu-button {
    background-color: white;
    border: 1px solid var(--snv-graphic-blue-light);
}

#snv-graphic-measure .snv-submenu-button:hover,
#snv-graphic-measure .btn-active {
    background-color: var(--snv-graphic-blue-light);
}

#snv-graphic-evaluate .snv-submenu-button {
    background-color: white;
    border: 1px solid var(--snv-graphic-yellow-light);
}

#snv-graphic-evaluate .snv-submenu-button:hover,
#snv-graphic-evaluate .btn-active {
    background-color: var(--snv-graphic-yellow-light);
}

/* SVG classes */
.st0{fill:none;}
.st1{fill:none;stroke:#FAE1A5;stroke-miterlimit:10;}
.st2{fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-linecap:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;}
.st3{font-size:18px;}
.st4{font-size:14px;}
.st5{fill:#1E2124;}
.st6{font-size:12px;}
.st7{fill:#FF8C14;}
.st8{fill:#B914FF;}
.st9{fill:#F02878;}
.st10{fill:#6E7682;}
.st11{fill:#00C43C;}
.st12{fill:#FFFFFF;}
.st13{fill:#FAE1A5;}
.st14{fill:#FFFFFF;stroke:#000000;stroke-miterlimit:10;}
.st15{fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-linecap:round;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:16.6667;}
.st16{font-size:10px;}
.st17{fill:#B914FF;stroke:#B914FF;stroke-miterlimit:10;}
.st18{fill:#EFC5DC;}
.st19{fill:#F9F1CA;}
.st20{fill:none;stroke:#1E2124;stroke-width:0.5;stroke-miterlimit:10;}
.st21{fill:none;stroke:#F02878;stroke-miterlimit:10;}
.st22{fill:none;stroke:#FFC850;stroke-linecap:round;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:16.6667;}
.st23{fill:#1E2124;}
.st24{fill:none;stroke:#1E2124;stroke-width:1.5;stroke-miterlimit:10;}
.st25{fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-width:1.5;stroke-linecap:round;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:16.6667;}
.st26{fill:none;stroke:#FAE1A5;stroke-linecap:round;stroke-linejoin:round;}
.st28{fill:none;stroke:#1E2124;stroke-miterlimit:10;}
.st30{fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-linecap:round;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-miterlimit:16.6667;}
.st32{stroke:#1E2124;stroke-linecap:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;}
.st34{fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-miterlimit:10;}
.st35{fill:none;stroke:#000000;stroke-linecap:round;stroke-miterlimit:10;}

@media screen and (min-width: 800px) {
    #snv-graphic-main {
        width: 100%;
        padding-top: 40px;
    }

    .snv-submenu-button {
        width: calc( (100% - 48px) / 4 );
    }

    .header-max button {
        height: 100px;
    }

    .snv-graphic-button-info {
        display: block;
    }

    .snv-graphic-main-container {
        flex-direction: row;
    }

    .snv-graphic-sidebar {
        width: 25%;
    }

    .snv-graphic-content {
        width: calc(75% - 16px);
    }

    #snv-graphic-header > .snv-graphic-button-wrapper {
        width: calc( (100% - 48px) / 4 );
    }

    .snv-graphic-layer select {
        width: calc( (100% - 48px) / 4 );
    }

    .snv-graphic-arrow {
        height: 100px;
    }
}
</style>
<div id="snv-graphic-container">
<button class="snv-graphic-start-item item-top layer-show">
    <strong>Prerequisite:</strong> Decide which platform and systemic risk to audit
    <div class="snv-graphic-arrow arrow-down"><span></span></div>
</button>
<button class="snv-graphic-start-item item-bottom layer-show">
    <strong>Result:</strong> Audit report
    <div class="snv-graphic-arrow arrow-up"><span></span></div>
</button>
<div id="snv-graphic-header" class="header-max">
    <div class="snv-graphic-button-wrapper snv-graphic-btn snv-graphic-btn-orange-light">
        <button onclick="minimizeHeader('snv-graphic-plan', this)" class=" snv-graphic-icon-btn">
            <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 24 24"><g id="b"><path d="m19,15.25c-1.81,0-3.33,1.29-3.67,3h-6.65c-.09-.42-.25-.81-.47-1.17l8.88-8.88c.56.34,1.22.55,1.92.55,2.07,0,3.75-1.68,3.75-3.75s-1.68-3.75-3.75-3.75c-1.81,0-3.33,1.29-3.67,3h-6.65c-.35-1.71-1.86-3-3.67-3-2.07,0-3.75,1.68-3.75,3.75s1.68,3.75,3.75,3.75c1.81,0,3.33-1.29,3.67-3h6.65c.11.53.34,1.02.65,1.44L7.19,15.97c-.62-.45-1.37-.72-2.19-.72-2.07,0-3.75,1.68-3.75,3.75s1.68,3.75,3.75,3.75c1.81,0,3.33-1.29,3.67-3h6.65c.35,1.71,1.86,3,3.67,3,2.07,0,3.75-1.68,3.75-3.75s-1.68-3.75-3.75-3.75ZM5,7.25c-1.24,0-2.25-1.01-2.25-2.25s1.01-2.25,2.25-2.25,2.25,1.01,2.25,2.25-1.01,2.25-2.25,2.25Zm14-4.5c1.24,0,2.25,1.01,2.25,2.25s-1.01,2.25-2.25,2.25-2.25-1.01-2.25-2.25,1.01-2.25,2.25-2.25ZM5,21.25c-1.24,0-2.25-1.01-2.25-2.25s1.01-2.25,2.25-2.25,2.25,1.01,2.25,2.25-1.01,2.25-2.25,2.25Zm14,0c-1.24,0-2.25-1.01-2.25-2.25s1.01-2.25,2.25-2.25,2.25,1.01,2.25,2.25-1.01,2.25-2.25,2.25Z"></path></g></svg>                    <span>Plan</span>
        </button>
        <div class="snv-graphic-button-info">Identify stakeholders and map out the audit process</div>
    </div>
    <div class="snv-graphic-button-wrapper snv-graphic-btn snv-graphic-btn-pink-light">
        <button onclick="minimizeHeader('snv-graphic-scenarios', this)" class="snv-graphic-icon-btn">
            <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 24 24"><g id="b"><path d="m20.1,8.87h-1.2c.02-.07.04-.13.04-.2v-.95c0-1.46-1.19-2.65-2.65-2.65h-1.2c.02-.07.04-.13.04-.2v-.95c0-1.46-1.19-2.65-2.65-2.65H3.9c-1.46,0-2.65,1.19-2.65,2.65v8.57c0,1.46,1.19,2.65,2.65,2.65h.95c.07,0,.14-.02.2-.04v1.2c0,1.46,1.19,2.65,2.65,2.65h.95c.07,0,.14-.02.2-.04v1.2c0,1.46,1.19,2.65,2.65,2.65h8.57c1.46,0,2.65-1.19,2.65-2.65v-8.57c0-1.46-1.19-2.65-2.65-2.65Zm-15.04-1.15v5.96c-.07-.02-.13-.04-.2-.04h-.95c-.64,0-1.15-.52-1.15-1.15V3.9c0-.64.52-1.15,1.15-1.15h8.57c.64,0,1.15.52,1.15,1.15v.95c0,.07.02.14.04.2h-5.96c-1.46,0-2.65,1.19-2.65,2.65Zm3.81,3.81v5.96c-.07-.02-.13-.04-.2-.04h-.95c-.64,0-1.15-.52-1.15-1.15V7.71c0-.64.52-1.15,1.15-1.15h8.57c.64,0,1.15.52,1.15,1.15v.95c0,.07.02.14.04.2h-5.96c-1.46,0-2.65,1.19-2.65,2.65Zm12.38,8.57c0,.64-.52,1.15-1.15,1.15h-8.57c-.64,0-1.15-.52-1.15-1.15v-8.57c0-.64.52-1.15,1.15-1.15h8.57c.64,0,1.15.52,1.15,1.15v8.57Z"></path></g></svg>                    <span>Scenarios</span>
        </button>
        <div class="snv-graphic-button-info">Define and prioritise risk scenarios</div>
    </div>
    <div class="snv-graphic-button-wrapper snv-graphic-btn snv-graphic-btn-blue-light">
        <button onclick="minimizeHeader('snv-graphic-measure', this)" class="snv-graphic-icon-btn">
            <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 24 24"><g id="b"><g><path d="m12,1.25C6.07,1.25,1.25,6.07,1.25,12s4.82,10.75,10.75,10.75,10.75-4.82,10.75-10.75S17.93,1.25,12,1.25Zm0,20c-5.1,0-9.25-4.15-9.25-9.25S6.9,2.75,12,2.75s9.25,4.15,9.25,9.25-4.15,9.25-9.25,9.25Z"></path><path d="m15.38,5.58l-2.97,4.46c-.13-.03-.27-.04-.4-.04-1.1,0-2,.9-2,2s.9,2,2,2,2-.9,2-2c0-.42-.13-.81-.35-1.13l2.97-4.46c.23-.34.14-.81-.21-1.04s-.81-.14-1.04.21Z"></path></g></g></svg><span>Measure</span>
        </button>
        <div class="snv-graphic-button-info">Define and prioritise measurements to observe risk scenarios</div>
    </div>
    <div class="snv-graphic-button-wrapper snv-graphic-btn snv-graphic-btn-yellow-light">
        <button onclick="minimizeHeader('snv-graphic-evaluate', this)" class="snv-graphic-icon-btn">
            <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 24 24"><g id="b"><path d="m22.53,21.47l-6.22-6.22c1.24-1.48,2-3.39,2-5.47,0-4.7-3.83-8.53-8.53-8.53S1.25,5.08,1.25,9.78s3.83,8.53,8.53,8.53c2.08,0,3.99-.75,5.47-2l6.22,6.22c.15.15.34.22.53.22s.38-.07.53-.22c.29-.29.29-.77,0-1.06ZM2.75,9.78c0-3.88,3.15-7.03,7.03-7.03s7.03,3.15,7.03,7.03-3.15,7.03-7.03,7.03-7.03-3.15-7.03-7.03Z"></path></g></svg>
            <span>Evaluate</span>
        </button>
        <div class="snv-graphic-button-info">Analyse results and create a report</div>
    </div>
</div>
<div id="snv-graphic-main" class="main-hide">
    <div id="snv-graphic-plan" class="snv-graphic-layer layer-hide">
        <div class="snv-graphic-submenu">
            <button class="snv-submenu-button btn-active" onclick="showPanel('snv-graphic-plan-understand', this)">Understand platform</button>
            <button class="snv-submenu-button" onclick="showPanel('snv-graphic-plan-define', this)">Define stakeholder</button>
        </div>
        <div class="snv-graphic-main-container">
            <div class="snv-graphic-sidebar">
                <p>
                    Get a good <strong>understanding</strong> of the platform. Use this information to determine the profiles of <strong>stakeholders</strong> who should be involved in the process. Depending on the experience and expertise needed, stakeholders could be platform developers, researchers, legal experts and representatives of the parties affected.
                </p>
                <a href="https://www.stiftung-nv.de/de/publication/auditing-recommender-systems#step1-planning" target="_blank">More details</a>
            </div>
            <div class="snv-graphic-content">
                <div id="snv-graphic-plan-understand" class="snv-graphic-panel layer-show">
                    <!--?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?-->
                    <svg version="1.1" id="plan-understand" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" x="0px" y="0px" viewBox="0 0 500 376.5" style="enable-background:new 0 0 500 376.5;" xml:space="preserve">
                    <g style="opacity: 0.5;">
                        <polygon class="st1" points="249.4,328.6 487.1,189.8 250.1,53 12.4,190.5    "></polygon>
                        <polygon class="st1" points="330.2,254.1 413.9,205.2 274.6,125.9 190.9,174.2    "></polygon>
                        <polygon class="st1" points="295.7,273.8 320.1,259.5 180.8,180.2 156.4,194  "></polygon>
                        <polygon class="st1" points="261.1,293.6 285.5,279.3 146.2,199.9 121.8,213.7    "></polygon>
                        <line class="st1" x1="455.8" y1="207.9" x2="218.9" y2="71.1"></line>
                        <line class="st1" x1="71.7" y1="223.2" x2="278.1" y2="104"></line>
                    </g>
                    <g class="snv-graphic-element">
                        <circle class="snv-graphic-element-btn snv-graphic-element-yellow" cx="51.5" cy="190.5" r="50"></circle>
                        <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 31 194.7802)" class="st3 st4">Media</text>
                        <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 118.7122 186.9687)" class="snv-graphic-element-text"><tspan x="0" y="0" class="st5 st3 st6">What type of media </tspan><tspan x="0" y="14.4" class="st5 st3 st6">is the platform based on?</tspan></text>
                    </g>
                    <g class="snv-graphic-element">
                        <circle class="snv-graphic-element-btn snv-graphic-element-blue" cx="258.5" cy="323.5" r="50"></circle>
                        <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 228.5448 327.7802)" class="st3 st4">Audience</text>
                        <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 325.4998 319.9686)" class="snv-graphic-element-text"><tspan x="0" y="0" class="st5 st3 st6">What is the audience </tspan><tspan x="0" y="14.4" class="st5 st3 st6">of the platform?</tspan></text>
                    </g>
                    <g class="snv-graphic-element">
                        <circle class="snv-graphic-element-btn snv-graphic-element-orange" cx="448.5" cy="190.5" r="50"></circle>
                        <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 418.8267 194.7803)" class="st3 st4">Products</text>
                        <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 250 186.9686)" class="snv-graphic-element-text"><tspan x="0" y="0" class="st5 st3 st6">What technical products</tspan><tspan x="-4" y="14.4" class="st5 st3 st6">do exist on the platform?</tspan></text>
                    </g>
                    <g class="snv-graphic-element">
                        <circle class="snv-graphic-element-btn snv-graphic-element-pink" cx="258.5" cy="52.5" r="50"></circle>
                        <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 230.5 56.7803)" class="st3 st4">Strategy</text>
                        <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 75 48.9688)" class="snv-graphic-element-text"><tspan x="0" y="0" class="st5 st3 st6">What is the platformâ€˜s</tspan><tspan x="38" y="14.4" class="st5 st3 st6">main strategy?</tspan></text>
                    </g>
                    </svg>
                </div>
                <div id="snv-graphic-plan-define" class="snv-graphic-panel layer-hide">
                    <!--?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?-->
                    <svg version="1.1" id="plan-understand" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" x="0px" y="0px" viewBox="0 0 500 376.5" style="enable-background:new 0 0 500 376.5;" xml:space="preserve">
                    <line class="st1" x1="403.5" y1="133.5" x2="311.9" y2="51.6"></line>
                    <line class="st1" x1="358.1" y1="309.9" x2="408.9" y2="205"></line>
                    <line class="st1" x1="189.2" y1="337.8" x2="321" y2="337.8"></line>
                    <line class="st1" x1="102.6" y1="205" x2="153.5" y2="309.9"></line>
                    <line class="st1" x1="199.4" y1="51.7" x2="108.1" y2="133.5"></line>
                    <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 214 42)" class="st4">Legal experts</text>
                    <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 394 180)" class="st4">Platforms</text>
                    <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 48 180)" class="st4"><tspan x="0" y="0">Users and </tspan><tspan x="-7" y="16.8">civil society</tspan></text>
                    <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 306 365)" class="st4">Researchers</text>
                    <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 84 365)" class="st4">Independent contractors</text>
                    <g>
                        <path class="st2" d="M164.7,340.7h-9.9l0-4.3c0-1.1,0.9-2,1.9-2h9.2"></path>
                        <g>
                            <g>
                                <circle class="st2" cx="161" cy="330.7" r="2.8"></circle>
                            </g>
                        </g>
                        <g>
                            <g>
                                <path class="st2" d="M172.3,343.9h-6c-0.4,0-0.8-0.4-0.8-0.8v-6c0-0.4,0.4-0.8,0.8-0.8h6c0.4,0,0.8,0.4,0.8,0.8v6
                                    C173.1,343.5,172.8,343.9,172.3,343.9z"></path>
                            </g>
                            <path class="st2" d="M163.8,336.9l5.1-4.7c0.4-0.4,1.1-0.4,1.5,0.1l4.4,4.7"></path>
                        </g>
                    </g>
                    <g>
                        <path class="st2" d="M348.9,339.4H339l0-4.3c0-1.1,0.9-2,1.9-2h8.6c1.1,0,1.9,0.9,1.9,2v0.7"></path>
                        <g>
                            <g>
                                <circle class="st2" cx="345.2" cy="329.3" r="2.8"></circle>
                            </g>
                        </g>
                        <g>
                            <path class="st2" d="M351.6,342.3h-2c-0.2,0-0.4-0.2-0.4-0.4v-5.2c0-0.2,0.2-0.4,0.4-0.4h2c0.2,0,0.4,0.2,0.4,0.4v5.2
                                C352.1,342.1,351.9,342.3,351.6,342.3z"></path>
                            <path class="st2" d="M354.5,342.3h-1.8c-0.3,0-0.6-0.2-0.6-0.6v-8.3c0-0.3,0.2-0.6,0.6-0.6h1.8c0.3,0,0.6,0.2,0.6,0.6v8.3
                                C355,342.1,354.8,342.3,354.5,342.3z"></path>
                            <path class="st2" d="M357.5,342.3h-1.9c-0.3,0-0.5-0.2-0.5-0.5v-6.6c0-0.3,0.2-0.5,0.5-0.5h1.9c0.3,0,0.5,0.2,0.5,0.5v6.6
                                C358,342.1,357.8,342.3,357.5,342.3z"></path>
                        </g>
                    </g>
                    <g>
                        <g>
                            <path class="st2" d="M251.8,16.3l-6.1-0.1l0-4.4c0-1.1,0.9-2,1.9-2h8.7c0.3,0,0.5,0.1,0.8,0.2"></path>
                            <circle class="st2" cx="252" cy="5.7" r="3.1"></circle>
                        </g>
                        <g>
                            <path class="st2" d="M257.6,11l-0.3-0.6c-0.2-0.3-0.1-0.6,0.2-0.8l3.3-1.9c0.3-0.2,0.6-0.1,0.8,0.2l0.3,0.6
                                c0.2,0.3,0.1,0.6-0.2,0.8l-3.3,1.9C258.1,11.3,257.8,11.2,257.6,11z"></path>
                            <path class="st2" d="M259.9,13.7l-7.2,4.2c-0.4,0.2-0.9,0-1.1-0.4v0c-0.3-0.4-0.2-1,0.2-1.2l7.2-4.2"></path>
                            <path class="st2" d="M260.7,16.2l-0.3-0.6c-0.2-0.3-0.1-0.6,0.2-0.8l3.3-1.9c0.3-0.2,0.6-0.1,0.8,0.2l0.3,0.6
                                c0.2,0.3,0.1,0.6-0.2,0.8l-3.3,1.9C261.2,16.6,260.8,16.5,260.7,16.2z"></path>
                            <path class="st2" d="M259.1,20.3v-1.2c0-0.4,0.3-0.7,0.7-0.7h5.3c0.4,0,0.7,0.3,0.7,0.7v1.2H259.1z"></path>
                            <line class="st2" x1="258.7" y1="11.4" x2="260.6" y2="14.7"></line>
                            <line class="st2" x1="261.6" y1="9.4" x2="263.6" y2="12.9"></line>
                        </g>
                    </g>
                    <g>
                        <path class="st2" d="M82.7,149.3l-8.1-0.1c-1.1,0-1.9,0.9-1.9,2l0,4.3h7.6"></path>
                        <circle class="st2" cx="79.4" cy="145.4" r="3"></circle>
                        <path class="st2" d="M80.3,159.6l0-4.3c0-1.1,0.9-2,1.9-2h8.6c1.1,0,1.9,0.9,1.9,2v4.3H80.3z"></path>
                        <circle class="st2" cx="86.5" cy="149.4" r="3"></circle>
                        <path class="st2" d="M99.7,147.7h-2.3l-3,1.8v-1.8h-1.3c-0.9,0-1.7-0.8-1.7-1.7v-4.6c0-0.9,0.8-1.7,1.7-1.7h6.6
                            c0.9,0,1.7,0.8,1.7,1.7v4.6C101.4,146.9,100.7,147.7,99.7,147.7z"></path>
                        <g>
                            <line class="st2" x1="93.4" y1="145.2" x2="99.4" y2="145.2"></line>
                            <line class="st2" x1="93.4" y1="142.2" x2="99.4" y2="142.2"></line>
                        </g>
                    </g>
                    <g>
                        <path class="st2" d="M425.2,151l-5.3-3.3c-1.2-0.8-1.2-2.6,0-3.3l5.2-3.2c0.6-0.4,1.4-0.4,2,0l5.2,3.3c1.2,0.8,1.3,2.6,0,3.3
                            l-5.2,3.2C426.7,151.4,425.9,151.4,425.2,151z"></path>
                        <path class="st2" d="M431.6,148.6l1,0.6c1.2,0.8,1.3,2.6,0,3.3l-5.2,3.2c-0.6,0.4-1.4,0.4-2,0l-5.3-3.3c-1.2-0.8-1.2-2.6,0-3.3
                            l0.9-0.6"></path>
                        <path class="st2" d="M431.4,153.4l1.1,0.7c1.2,0.8,1.3,2.6,0,3.3l-5.2,3.2c-0.6,0.4-1.4,0.4-2,0l-5.3-3.3c-1.2-0.8-1.2-2.6,0-3.3
                            l1.2-0.7"></path>
                    </g>
                    </svg>
                </div>
            </div>
        </div>      
    </div>
    <div id="snv-graphic-scenarios" class="snv-graphic-layer layer-hide">
        <div class="snv-graphic-submenu">
            <button class="snv-submenu-button btn-active" onclick="showPanel('snv-graphic-scenarios-define', this)">Define scenarios</button>
            <button class="snv-submenu-button" onclick="showPanel('snv-graphic-scenarios-prioritize', this)">Prioritise scenarios</button>
        </div>
        <div class="snv-graphic-main-container">
            <div class="snv-graphic-sidebar">
                <p>
                    <strong>Define</strong> and <strong>prioritise</strong> scenarios. A scenario is a description of specific issues related to a 'systemic risk'. It breaks down abstract risks into concrete testable hypotheses by defining the affected party and its characteristics, the harm, the involved elements of the platform and the further impact. A systemic risk may often involve several scenarios; therefore, selecting scenarios and deciding if they have a 'high' priority is necessary. 
                </p>
                <a href="https://www.stiftung-nv.de/de/publication/auditing-recommender-systems#step2-scenarios" target="_blank">More details</a>
            </div>
            <div class="snv-graphic-content">
                <div id="snv-graphic-scenarios-define" class="snv-graphic-panel layer-show">
                    <!--?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?-->
                    <svg version="1.1" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" x="0px" y="0px" viewBox="0 0 500 376.5" style="enable-background:new 0 0 500 376.5;" xml:space="preserve">
                    <g id="scenarios-define-01">
                        <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 63.5789 14.2822)"><tspan x="0" y="0" class="st7 st3">An individual/group/institution</tspan><tspan x="255.8" y="0" class="st3"> </tspan><tspan x="259.9" y="0" class="st8 st3">defined by </tspan><tspan x="0" y="56" class="st8 st3">some characteristics</tspan><tspan x="174.9" y="56" class=" st3"> </tspan><tspan x="179" y="56" class="st9  st3">has experienced a </tspan><tspan x="0" y="112" class="st9  st3">harm</tspan><tspan x="43.3" y="112" class=" st3"> </tspan><tspan x="47.5" y="112" class="st10  st3">that is related to something happening </tspan><tspan x="0" y="168" class="st10  st3">on the platform</tspan><tspan x="128.6" y="168" class=" st3"> and </tspan><tspan x="168.1" y="168" class="st11  st3">this also has macro </tspan><tspan x="0" y="224" class="st11  st3">impact.</tspan></text>
                    </g>
                    <g id="scenarios-define-02">
                        <g>
                            <rect x="63.6" y="1.7" class="st0" width="373.4" height="306.5"></rect>
                            <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 63.5967 14.7124)"><tspan x="0" y="0" class="st3 st7">A young adult </tspan><tspan x="116.7" y="0" class="st8 st3">who is temporarily in a personal crisis </tspan><tspan x="0" y="56" class="st9  st3">is overly exposed to videos describing </tspan><tspan x="0" y="112" class="st9  st3">or showing self-harm</tspan><tspan x="176.5" y="112" class=" st3"> </tspan><tspan x="180.7" y="112" class="st10  st3">by the recommender </tspan><tspan x="0" y="168" class="st10  st3">system of the 'ForYou' feed</tspan><tspan x="224.1" y="168" class=" st3"> and </tspan><tspan x="263.7" y="168" class="st11  st3">this might </tspan><tspan x="0" y="224" class="st11  st3">exacerbate the general mental health crisis of </tspan><tspan x="0" y="280" class="st11  st3">young adults.</tspan></text>
                        </g>
                        <g>
                            <rect x="64" y="23" class="st7" width="90" height="18"></rect>
                            <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 69.665 35.832)" class="st12 st6 st10">affected party</text>
                        </g>
                        <g>
                            <rect x="182" y="23" class="st8" width="90" height="18"></rect>
                            <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 188.2588 35.832)" class="st12 st6 st10">characteristic</text>
                        </g>
                        <g>
                            <rect x="64" y="79" class="st9" width="44" height="18"></rect>
                            <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 71.0527 91.832)" class="st12 st6 st10">harm</text>
                        </g>
                        <g>
                            <rect x="245" y="136" class="st10" width="130" height="18"></rect>
                            <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 250.251 148.832)" class="st12 st6 st10">platform involvement</text>
                        </g>
                        <g>
                            <rect x="325" y="191" class="st11" width="90" height="18"></rect>
                            <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 331.8223 203.832)" class="st12 st6 st10">macro impact</text>
                        </g>
                    </g>
                    </svg>
                </div>
                <div id="snv-graphic-scenarios-prioritize" class="snv-graphic-panel layer-hide">
                    <!--?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?-->
                    <svg version="1.1" id="scenarios-prioritize" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" x="0px" y="0px" viewBox="0 0 500 376.5" style="enable-background:new 0 0 500 376.5;" xml:space="preserve">
                    <g>
                        <g>
                            <rect x="415.7" y="2.9" class="st13" width="10" height="247"></rect>
                        </g>
                        <g>
                            <rect x="389.4" y="2.9" class="st13" width="9.3" height="247"></rect>
                        </g>
                        <g>
                            <rect x="363.2" y="2.9" class="st13" width="8.6" height="247"></rect>
                        </g>
                        <g>
                            <rect x="337" y="2.9" class="st13" width="7.9" height="247"></rect>
                        </g>
                        <g>
                            <rect x="310.8" y="2.9" class="st13" width="7.2" height="247"></rect>
                        </g>
                        <g>
                            <rect x="284.5" y="2.9" class="st13" width="6.5" height="247"></rect>
                        </g>
                        <g>
                            <rect x="258.3" y="2.9" class="st13" width="5.8" height="247"></rect>
                        </g>
                        <g>
                            <rect x="232.1" y="2.9" class="st13" width="5.2" height="247"></rect>
                        </g>
                        <g>
                            <rect x="205.8" y="2.9" class="st13" width="4.5" height="247"></rect>
                        </g>
                        <g>
                            <rect x="179.6" y="2.9" class="st13" width="3.8" height="247"></rect>
                        </g>
                        <g>
                            <rect x="153.4" y="2.9" class="st13" width="3.1" height="247"></rect>
                        </g>
                        <g>
                            <rect x="127.1" y="2.9" class="st13" width="2.4" height="247"></rect>
                        </g>
                        <g>
                            <rect x="100.9" y="2.9" class="st13" width="1.7" height="247"></rect>
                        </g>
                        <g>
                            <rect x="74.7" y="2.9" class="st13" width="1" height="247"></rect>
                        </g>
                    </g>
                    <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 72.9999 276.3171)" class="st4">Normal priority</text>
                    <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 345 276.3171)" class="st4">High priority</text>
                    <g>
                        <rect x="188.7" y="85.4" class="st14" width="141" height="108"></rect>
                        <rect x="178.7" y="75.4" class="st14" width="141" height="108"></rect>
                        <rect x="168.7" y="65.4" class="st14" width="141" height="108"></rect>
                    </g>
                    <rect x="255.2" y="85.9" class="st8" width="43" height="5"></rect>
                    <rect x="184.2" y="85.9" class="st11" width="65" height="5"></rect>
                    <rect x="255.2" y="130.9" class="st11" width="31" height="5"></rect>
                    <rect x="184.2" y="130.9" class="st10" width="65" height="5"></rect>
                    <rect x="184.2" y="145.9" class="st11" width="88" height="5"></rect>
                    <rect x="184.2" y="100.9" class="st7" width="90" height="5"></rect>
                    <rect x="184.2" y="115.9" class="st9" width="107" height="5"></rect>
                    <path class="st15" d="M161.7,125.7h-25.1 M146.1,115.7l-10,10l10,10"></path>
                    <path class="st15" d="M337.1,125.7h25.1 M352.6,135.8l10-10l-10-10"></path>
                    </svg>
                </div>
            </div>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div id="snv-graphic-measure" class="snv-graphic-layer layer-hide">
        <div class="snv-graphic-submenu">
            <button class="snv-submenu-button btn-active" onclick="showPanel('snv-graphic-measure-audits', this)">Types of audits</button>
            <button class="snv-submenu-button" onclick="showPanel('snv-graphic-measure-prioritize', this)">Prioritise</button>
        </div>
        <div class="snv-graphic-main-container">
            <div class="snv-graphic-sidebar">
                <p>
                    Develop measurements to understand the scenario. There are different <strong>types of algorithm audits</strong>, as well as <strong>platform elements</strong> to consider. These can range from automated measurements that look at the actual implementation to user perspectives through surveys. 
                    An auditor needs to develop multiple measurements and then prioritise them to find the best measurement(s) to test a specific scenario.                             
                </p>
                <a href="https://www.stiftung-nv.de/de/publication/auditing-recommender-systems#step3-measurements" target="_blank">More details</a>
            </div>
            <div class="snv-graphic-content">
                <div id="snv-graphic-measure-audits" class="snv-graphic-panel layer-show">
                    <div id="snv-graphic-measure-audits-header">
                        <p>Select audit type or platform element:</p>
                        <select id="snv-graphic-measure-select" class="measure-audit" onchange="showElements(this)">
                            <optgroup id="audits" label="Types of audits">
                                <option value="code-audit">Code audit</option>
                                <option value="crowd-audit">Crowd-sourced audit</option>
                                <option value="document-audit">Document audit</option>
                                <option value="architecture-audit">Architecture audit</option>
                                <option value="automated-audit">Automated audit</option>
                                <option value="user-survey">User survey</option>
                            </optgroup>
                            <optgroup id="elements" label="Platform elements">
                                <option value="user-experience">User experience</option>
                                <option value="user-interface">User interface</option>
                                <option value="algorithmic-logic">Algorithmic logic</option>
                                <option value="content-moderation">Content moderation</option>
                                <option value="terms-conditions">Terms and conditions</option>
                                <option value="advertisement">Advertisement</option>
                                <option value="report-mechanisms">Report mechanisms</option>
                                <option value="data-practices">Data-related practices</option>
                            </optgroup>
                        </select>
                    </div>
                    <div id="snv-graphic-measure-audits-body">
                        <p id="snv-graphic-measure-audits-body-title">Connected elements</p>
                        <div class="snv-graphic-measure-element layer-hide data-practices algorithmic-logic">
                            <div class="snv-graphic-measure-button measure-audit">
                                Code audit
                            </div>
                            <div id="code-audit-text" class="snv-graphic-measure-text">
                                Text
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div class="snv-graphic-measure-element layer-hide user-experience algorithmic-logic advertisement">
                            <div class="snv-graphic-measure-button measure-audit">
                                Crowd-sourced audit
                            </div>
                            <div id="crowd-audit-text" class="snv-graphic-measure-text">
                                Text
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div class="snv-graphic-measure-element layer-hide terms-conditions user-interface data-practices content-moderation">
                            <div class="snv-graphic-measure-button measure-audit">
                                Document audit
                            </div>
                            <div id="document-audit-text" class="snv-graphic-measure-text">
                                Text
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div class="snv-graphic-measure-element layer-hide content-moderation report-mechanisms">
                            <div class="snv-graphic-measure-button measure-audit">
                                Architecture audit
                            </div>
                            <div id="architecture-audit-text" class="snv-graphic-measure-text">
                                Text
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div class="snv-graphic-measure-element layer-hide user-interface content-moderation algorithmic-logic advertisement">
                            <div class="snv-graphic-measure-button measure-audit">
                                Automated audit
                            </div>
                            <div id="automated-audit-text" class="snv-graphic-measure-text">
                                Text
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div class="snv-graphic-measure-element layer-hide user-experience user-interface report-mechanisms">
                            <div class="snv-graphic-measure-button measure-audit">
                                User survey
                            </div>
                            <div id="survey-audit-text" class="snv-graphic-measure-text">
                                Text
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div class="snv-graphic-measure-element layer-hide crowd-audit user-survey">
                            <div class="snv-graphic-measure-button measure-element">
                                User experience
                            </div>
                            <div id="experience-element-text" class="snv-graphic-measure-text">
                                Text
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div class="snv-graphic-measure-element layer-hide document-audit user-survey automated-audit">
                            <div class="snv-graphic-measure-button measure-element">
                                User interface
                            </div>
                            <div id="interface-element-text" class="snv-graphic-measure-text">
                                Text
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div class="snv-graphic-measure-element code-audit crowd-audit automated-audit">
                            <div class="snv-graphic-measure-button measure-element">
                                Algorithmic logic
                            </div>
                            <div id="logic-element-text" class="snv-graphic-measure-text">
                                Review source code, evaluate model parameters.
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div class="snv-graphic-measure-element layer-hide document-audit architecture-audit automated-audit">
                            <div class="snv-graphic-measure-button measure-element">
                                Content moderation
                            </div>
                            <div id="content-element-text" class="snv-graphic-measure-text">
                                Text
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div class="snv-graphic-measure-element layer-hide document-audit">
                            <div class="snv-graphic-measure-button measure-element">
                                Terms and conditions
                            </div>
                            <div id="terms-element-text" class="snv-graphic-measure-text">
                                Text
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div class="snv-graphic-measure-element layer-hide crowd-audit automated-audit">
                            <div class="snv-graphic-measure-button measure-element">
                                Advertisement
                            </div>
                            <div id="advertisement-element-text" class="snv-graphic-measure-text">
                                Text
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div class="snv-graphic-measure-element layer-hide architecture-audit user-survey">
                            <div class="snv-graphic-measure-button measure-element">
                                Report mechanisms
                            </div>
                            <div id="report-element-text" class="snv-graphic-measure-text">
                                Text
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div class="snv-graphic-measure-element code-audit document-audit">
                            <div class="snv-graphic-measure-button measure-element">
                                Data-related practices
                            </div>
                            <div id="data-element-text" class="snv-graphic-measure-text">
                                Check dataflows, ensure that sensitive data like ethnicity is not used as model input.
                            </div>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div id="snv-graphic-measure-prioritize" class="snv-graphic-panel layer-hide">
                    <!--?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?-->
                    <svg version="1.1" id="measure-prioritize" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" x="0px" y="0px" viewBox="0 0 500 376.5" style="enable-background:new 0 0 500 376.5;" xml:space="preserve">
                    <g>
                        <circle class="st17" cx="249.6" cy="241.3" r="50"></circle>
                        <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 221.4787 236.893)"><tspan x="0" y="0" class="st12 st4">Measure </tspan><tspan x="4.5" y="16.8" class="st12 st4">Priority</tspan></text>
                    </g>
                    <g>
                        <g>
                            <g>
                                <polyline class="st20" points="249.1,178.7 249.1,128.8 217.1,96.8           "></polyline>
                                <g>
                                    <polygon class="st5" points="251.6,178 249.1,182.3 246.6,178                "></polygon>
                                </g>
                            </g>
                        </g>
                    </g>
                    <g>
                        <g>
                            <polyline class="st20" points="249.1,178.7 249.1,129.3 281.1,97.3       "></polyline>
                            <g>
                                <polygon class="st5" points="251.6,178 249.1,182.3 246.6,178            "></polygon>
                            </g>
                        </g>
                    </g>
                    <g class="snv-graphic-measure-prioritize-container">
                        <circle class="snv-graphic-element-btn snv-graphic-element-pink" cx="320.1" cy="51.3" r="50"></circle>
                        <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 277.9904 56.393)" class="st4">Detectability</text>
                        <g class="snv-graphic-measure-prioritize-element">
                            <circle class="st18" cx="388.6" cy="119.3" r="30"></circle>
                            <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 371.5629 117.3896)"><tspan x="-3" y="0" class="st16">Platform</tspan><tspan x="-4.6" y="12" class=" st16">influence</tspan></text>
                        </g>
                        <g class="snv-graphic-measure-prioritize-element">
                            <circle class="st18" cx="320.6" cy="146.3" r="30"></circle>
                            <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 305.9924 144.3896)"><tspan x="0" y="0" class="st16">Macro</tspan><tspan x="-4" y="12" class=" st16"> Effects</tspan></text>
                        </g>
                        <g class="snv-graphic-measure-prioritize-element">
                            <circle class="st18" cx="418.6" cy="54.3" r="30"></circle>
                            <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 394.8478 52.3896)"><tspan x="0" y="0" class="st16">Individual </tspan><tspan x="11.7" y="12" class=" st16">harm</tspan></text>
                        </g>
                        <text class="snv-graphic-measure-prioritize-text st4" transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 337.2692 220.4986)"><tspan x="8" y="0" class="st5">How can a scenario</tspan><tspan x="-2.2" y="14.4" class="st5">be effectively detected</tspan><tspan x="-5" y="28.8" class="st5">with this measurement?</tspan></text>
                    </g>
                    <g class="snv-graphic-measure-prioritize-container">
                        <circle class="snv-graphic-element-btn snv-graphic-element-yellow" cx="180.1" cy="51.3" r="50"></circle>
                        <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 147.9811 56.393)" class="st4">Difficulty</text>
                        <g class="snv-graphic-measure-prioritize-element">
                            <circle class="st19" cx="81.4" cy="54" r="30"></circle>
                            <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 66.4328 45.3896)"><tspan x="0" y="0" class="st16">Imple-</tspan><tspan x="-9.8" y="12" class=" st16">mentation </tspan><tspan x="2.5" y="24" class=" st16">costs</tspan></text>
                        </g>
                        <g class="snv-graphic-measure-prioritize-element">
                            <circle class="st19" cx="111.4" cy="119" r="30"></circle>
                            <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 92.0581 117.3896)"><tspan x="0" y="0" class="st16">Replica-</tspan><tspan x="7.9" y="12" class=" st16">bility</tspan></text>
                        </g>
                        <g class="snv-graphic-measure-prioritize-element">
                            <circle class="st19" cx="179.4" cy="146" r="30"></circle>
                            <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 163.6574 138.3896)"><tspan x="0" y="0" class="st16">Repre-</tspan><tspan x="-7.8" y="12" class=" st16">sentative-</tspan><tspan x="5" y="24" class=" st16">ness</tspan></text>
                        </g>
                        <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 57.6593 229.4986)" class="snv-graphic-measure-prioritize-text st4"><tspan x="0" y="0" class="st5">How difficult will it </tspan><tspan x="2.9" y="14.4" class="st5">be to execute this </tspan><tspan x="11.9" y="28.8" class="st5 ">measurement?</tspan></text>
                    </g>
                    </svg>
                </div>
            </div>
        </div>
    </div>
    <div id="snv-graphic-evaluate" class="snv-graphic-layer layer-hide">
        <div class="snv-graphic-submenu">
            <button class="snv-submenu-button btn-active" onclick="showPanel('snv-graphic-evaluate-goals', this)">Goals</button>
            <button class="snv-submenu-button" onclick="showPanel('snv-graphic-evaluate-report', this)">Report</button>
        </div>
        <div class="snv-graphic-main-container">
            <div class="snv-graphic-sidebar">
                <p>
                    After conducting the measurements, you need to <strong>analyse</strong> the results and <strong>write</strong> an audit report. The report should foster observability and enable reproducibility and recommend mitigation measures. 
                </p>
                <a href="https://www.stiftung-nv.de/de/publication/auditing-recommender-systems#step4-evaluation-and-reporting" target="_blank">More details</a>
            </div>
            <div class="snv-graphic-content">
                <div id="snv-graphic-evaluate-goals" class="snv-graphic-panel layer-show">
                    <!--?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?-->
                    <svg version="1.1" id="measure-prioritize" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" x="0px" y="0px" viewBox="0 0 500 376.5" style="enable-background:new 0 0 500 376.5;" xml:space="preserve">
                    <g>
                        <circle class="st24" cx="248.6" cy="138.6" r="4.2"></circle>
                        <path class="st25" d="M257.6,132.1c1.3,1.8,2.1,4.1,2.1,6.5c0,6.1-5,11.1-11.1,11.1c-6.1,0-11.1-5-11.1-11.1c0-2.3,0.7-4.4,1.9-6.2"></path>
                        <path class="st25" d="M265.6,139.6c0,0-6.8,10.8-17,10.1c-10.4-0.6-17-10.1-17-10.1s6.6-10.1,17-10.1
                            C258.8,129.5,265.6,139.6,265.6,139.6z"></path>
                    </g>
                    <g>
                        <circle class="st25" cx="238.3" cy="204.5" r="4"></circle>
                        <path class="st25" d="M262.8,204.5c0,2.2-1.8,4-4,4s-4-1.8-4-4c0-2.2,1.8-4,4-4S262.8,202.3,262.8,204.5z"></path>
                        <path class="st25" d="M239.9,197.9c2-2.6,5.2-4.3,8.7-4.3c3.4,0,6.5,1.6,8.5,4"></path>
                        <path class="st25" d="M257.7,211c-2,2.9-5.3,4.8-9.1,4.8c-3.8,0-7.1-1.9-9.1-4.8"></path>
                        <polygon points="258.5,195.6 254.6,198.3 257.8,198.8    "></polygon>
                        <polygon points="238.1,213.1 242,210.4 238.8,210    "></polygon>
                    </g>
                    <g>
                        <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 212.0789 166.8727)" class="st6">Observability</text>
                    </g>
                    <g>
                        <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 204.5105 234.8726)" class="st6">Reproducibility</text>
                    </g>
                    <g>
                        <g>
                            <path class="st26" d="M278.5,43.6c55.6,8.6,99.9,51.4,110.7,106.2"></path>
                            <g>
                                <polygon class="st13" points="395,147.9 383.1,150.1 390.1,155           "></polygon>
                            </g>
                        </g>
                    </g>
                    <g>
                        <g>
                            <path class="st26" d="M283.6,327.5c54.9-10.7,97.7-55,106.5-110.5"></path>
                            <g>
                                <polygon class="st13" points="283.4,321.3 285.5,333.3 278.5,328.4           "></polygon>
                            </g>
                        </g>
                    </g>
                    <g>
                        <g>
                            <path class="st26" d="M106.3,222.1c10.9,54.8,55.1,97.6,110.7,106.2"></path>
                            <g>
                                <polygon class="st13" points="112.4,221.9 100.5,224 105.4,217           "></polygon>
                            </g>
                        </g>
                    </g>
                    <g>
                        <g>
                            <path class="st26" d="M212.7,44.3C157.5,54.7,114.2,99.1,105.4,155"></path>
                            <g>
                                <polygon class="st13" points="213,50.4 210.9,38.5 217.9,43.4            "></polygon>
                            </g>
                        </g>
                    </g>
                    <g class="snv-graphic-element">
                        <g>
                            <circle class="snv-graphic-element-orange" cx="247.8" cy="42" r="17"></circle>
                            <g>
                                <circle class="st28" cx="242.9" cy="37.1" r="2.1"></circle>
                                <circle class="st28" cx="252.7" cy="37.1" r="2.1"></circle>
                                <circle class="st28" cx="242.9" cy="46.9" r="2.1"></circle>
                                <circle class="st28" cx="252.7" cy="46.9" r="2.1"></circle>
                                <line class="st28" x1="245" y1="37.1" x2="250.6" y2="37.1"></line>
                                <line class="st28" x1="251.3" y1="38.6" x2="244.5" y2="45.5"></line>
                                <line class="st28" x1="245" y1="46.9" x2="250.6" y2="46.9"></line>
                            </g>
                        </g>
                        <text class="snv-graphic-element-text st6" transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 234.8736 12.3017)">Plan</text>
                    </g>
                    <g class="snv-graphic-element">
                        <g>
                            <circle class="snv-graphic-element-pink" cx="391.6" cy="186" r="17"></circle>
                            <g>
                                <path class="st30" d="M391.3,183.9h6c0.7,0,1.3,0.6,1.3,1.3v6c0,0.7-0.6,1.3-1.3,1.3h-6c-0.7,0-1.3-0.6-1.3-1.3v-6
                                    C389.9,184.5,390.5,183.9,391.3,183.9z"></path>
                                <path class="st30" d="M389.3,189.9h-0.7c-0.7,0-1.3-0.6-1.3-1.3v-6c0-0.7,0.6-1.3,1.3-1.3h6c0.7,0,1.3,0.6,1.3,1.3v0.7"></path>
                                <path class="st30" d="M386.6,187.3h-0.7c-0.7,0-1.3-0.6-1.3-1.3v-6c0-0.7,0.6-1.3,1.3-1.3h6c0.7,0,1.3,0.6,1.3,1.3v0.7"></path>
                            </g>
                        </g>
                        <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 418.6572 190.3017)" class="snv-graphic-element-text st6">Scenarios</text>
                    </g>
                    <g class="snv-graphic-element">
                        <g>
                            <circle class="snv-graphic-element-blue" cx="248.8" cy="328.2" r="17"></circle>
                            <g>
                                <circle class="st30" cx="248.8" cy="328.2" r="7"></circle>
                                <circle class="st23" cx="248.8" cy="328.2" r="1.4"></circle>
                                <line class="st32" x1="248.8" y1="328.2" x2="251.6" y2="324"></line>
                            </g>
                        </g>
                        <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 224.0777 364.3017)" class="snv-graphic-element-text st6">Measure</text>
                    </g>
                    <g class="snv-graphic-element">
                        <g>
                            <circle class="snv-graphic-element-yellow" cx="103.6" cy="186" r="17"></circle>
                            <g>
                                <circle class="st34" cx="102" cy="184.4" r="5.4"></circle>
                                <line class="st35" x1="105.9" y1="188.3" x2="110.6" y2="193"></line>
                            </g>
                        </g>
                        <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 26.0176 188.3017)" class="snv-graphic-element-text st6">Evaluate</text>
                    </g>
                    </svg>
                </div>
                <div id="snv-graphic-evaluate-report" class="snv-graphic-panel layer-hide">
                    <!--?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?-->
                    <svg version="1.1" id="measure-prioritize" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" x="0px" y="0px" viewBox="0 0 500 376.5" style="enable-background:new 0 0 500 376.5;" xml:space="preserve">
                    <g>
                        <g>
                            <path class="st26" d="M278.5,43.6c55.6,8.6,99.9,51.4,110.7,106.2"></path>
                            <g>
                                <polygon class="st13" points="395,147.9 383.1,150.1 390.1,155           "></polygon>
                            </g>
                        </g>
                    </g>
                    <g>
                        <g>
                            <path class="st26" d="M283.6,327.5c54.9-10.7,97.7-55,106.5-110.5"></path>
                            <g>
                                <polygon class="st13" points="283.4,321.3 285.5,333.3 278.5,328.4           "></polygon>
                            </g>
                        </g>
                    </g>
                    <g>
                        <g>
                            <path class="st26" d="M106.3,222.1c10.9,54.8,55.1,97.6,110.7,106.2"></path>
                            <g>
                                <polygon class="st13" points="112.4,221.9 100.5,224 105.4,217           "></polygon>
                            </g>
                        </g>
                    </g>
                    <g>
                        <g>
                            <path class="st26" d="M212.7,44.3C157.5,54.7,114.2,99.1,105.4,155"></path>
                            <g>
                                <polygon class="st13" points="213,50.4 210.9,38.5 217.9,43.4            "></polygon>
                            </g>
                        </g>
                    </g>
                    <g class="snv-graphic-element">
                        <g>
                            <circle class="snv-graphic-element-orange" cx="247.8" cy="42" r="17"></circle>
                            <g>
                                <circle class="st28" cx="242.9" cy="37.1" r="2.1"></circle>
                                <circle class="st28" cx="252.7" cy="37.1" r="2.1"></circle>
                                <circle class="st28" cx="242.9" cy="46.9" r="2.1"></circle>
                                <circle class="st28" cx="252.7" cy="46.9" r="2.1"></circle>
                                <line class="st28" x1="245" y1="37.1" x2="250.6" y2="37.1"></line>
                                <line class="st28" x1="251.3" y1="38.6" x2="244.5" y2="45.5"></line>
                                <line class="st28" x1="245" y1="46.9" x2="250.6" y2="46.9"></line>
                            </g>
                        </g>
                        <text class="snv-graphic-element-text st6" transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 234.8736 12.3017)">Plan</text>
                    </g>
                    <g class="snv-graphic-element">
                        <g>
                            <circle class="snv-graphic-element-pink" cx="391.6" cy="186" r="17"></circle>
                            <g>
                                <path class="st30" d="M391.3,183.9h6c0.7,0,1.3,0.6,1.3,1.3v6c0,0.7-0.6,1.3-1.3,1.3h-6c-0.7,0-1.3-0.6-1.3-1.3v-6
                                    C389.9,184.5,390.5,183.9,391.3,183.9z"></path>
                                <path class="st30" d="M389.3,189.9h-0.7c-0.7,0-1.3-0.6-1.3-1.3v-6c0-0.7,0.6-1.3,1.3-1.3h6c0.7,0,1.3,0.6,1.3,1.3v0.7"></path>
                                <path class="st30" d="M386.6,187.3h-0.7c-0.7,0-1.3-0.6-1.3-1.3v-6c0-0.7,0.6-1.3,1.3-1.3h6c0.7,0,1.3,0.6,1.3,1.3v0.7"></path>
                            </g>
                        </g>
                        <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 418.6572 190.3017)" class="snv-graphic-element-text st6">Scenarios</text>
                    </g>
                    <g class="snv-graphic-element">
                        <g>
                            <circle class="snv-graphic-element-blue" cx="248.8" cy="328.2" r="17"></circle>
                            <g>
                                <circle class="st30" cx="248.8" cy="328.2" r="7"></circle>
                                <circle class="st23" cx="248.8" cy="328.2" r="1.4"></circle>
                                <line class="st32" x1="248.8" y1="328.2" x2="251.6" y2="324"></line>
                            </g>
                        </g>
                        <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 224.0777 364.3017)" class="snv-graphic-element-text st6">Measure</text>
                    </g>
                    <g class="snv-graphic-element">
                        <g>
                            <circle class="snv-graphic-element-yellow" cx="103.6" cy="186" r="17"></circle>
                            <g>
                                <circle class="st34" cx="102" cy="184.4" r="5.4"></circle>
                                <line class="st35" x1="105.9" y1="188.3" x2="110.6" y2="193"></line>
                            </g>
                        </g>
                        <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 26.0176 188.3017)" class="snv-graphic-element-text st6">Evaluate</text>
                    </g>
                    <g>
                        <rect x="174.2" y="101.1" class="st14" width="154" height="171.6"></rect>
                        <rect x="170.2" y="97.8" class="st14" width="154" height="171.6"></rect>
                        <rect x="166.2" y="94.5" class="st14" width="154" height="171.6"></rect>
                    </g>
                    <g>
                        <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 178.7861 119.3564)" class="st5 st6">1)  Executive Summary</text>
                    </g>
                    <g>
                        <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 178.7861 145.3564)" class="st5 st6">2)  Introduction</text>
                    </g>
                    <g>
                        <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 178.7861 171.3564)" class="st5 st6">3)  Scenarios</text>
                    </g>
                    <g>
                        <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 178.7861 196.3564)" class="st5 st6">4)  Methods and</text>
                    </g>
                    <g>
                        <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 177.7861 235.3564)" class="st5 st6">5)  Results and</text>
                    </g>
                    <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 193 211.084)" class="st5 st6">Measurements</text>
                    <text transform="matrix(1 0 0 1 193 250.084)" class="st5 st6">Audit Opinion</text>
                    </svg>
                </div>
            </div>
        </div>
    </div>
</div>
</div>

<script lang="JavaScript">
    function minimizeHeader(element, button) {
    let header = document.getElementById('snv-graphic-header');
    let main = document.getElementById('snv-graphic-main');
    let layers = document.querySelectorAll('.snv-graphic-layer');
    let layer = document.getElementById(element);
    let submenu = layer.children[0];
    let buttons = document.querySelectorAll('.snv-graphic-icon-btn');
    let startItems = document.querySelectorAll('.snv-graphic-start-item');
    let panels = document.querySelectorAll('.snv-graphic-panel');
    let firstPanel = layer.getElementsByClassName('snv-graphic-panel')[0];
    
    header.classList.add('header-min');
    header.classList.remove('header-max');

    main.classList.add('main-show');
    main.classList.remove('main-hide');

    startItems.forEach(el=>el.classList.add('layer-hide'));
    startItems.forEach(el=>el.classList.remove('layer-show'));

    panels.forEach(el=>el.classList.add('layer-hide'));
    panels.forEach(el=>el.classList.remove('layer-show'));

    layers.forEach(el=>el.classList.add('layer-hide'));
    layers.forEach(el=>el.classList.remove('layer-show'));

    buttons.forEach(el=>el.classList.remove('btn-active'));
    button.classList.add('btn-active');

    layer.classList.remove('layer-hide');
    layer.classList.add('layer-show');

    for (const node of submenu.children) {
        node.classList.remove('btn-active');
    }
    submenu.children[0].classList.add('btn-active');

    firstPanel.classList.add('layer-show');
}

function showPanel(element, button) {
    let panels = document.querySelectorAll('.snv-graphic-panel');
    let panel = document.getElementById(element);
    let buttons = button.parentNode.children;

    panels.forEach(el=>el.classList.add('layer-hide'));
    panels.forEach(el=>el.classList.remove('layer-show'));
    
    for (const node of buttons) {
        node.classList.remove('btn-active');
    }

    button.classList.add('btn-active');

    panel.classList.add('layer-show');
}

function showElements(element) {
    let allElements = document.querySelectorAll('.snv-graphic-measure-element');
    let selectedOption = element.value;
    let className = "." + element.value;
    let connectedElements = document.querySelectorAll(className);
    let group = element.options[element.selectedIndex].parentNode.id;
    let textElement = document.getElementById('snv-graphic-measure-audits-body-title');

    if( group == "audits" ){
        element.classList.remove('measure-element');
        element.classList.add('measure-audit');
        textElement.innerHTML = "Connected elements";
    } else {
        element.classList.remove('measure-audit');
        element.classList.add('measure-element');
        textElement.innerHTML = "Connected audits";
    }

    if( selectedOption == "code-audit" ) {
        document.getElementById('data-element-text').innerHTML = "Check dataflows, ensure that sensitive data like ethnicity is not used as model input.";
        document.getElementById('logic-element-text').innerHTML = "Review source code, evaluate model parameters.";
    } else if ( selectedOption == "crowd-audit") {
        document.getElementById('experience-element-text').innerHTML = "Measure what platform elements users access most often.";
        document.getElementById('logic-element-text').innerHTML = "Measure exposure to specific (harmful) content.";
        document.getElementById('advertisement-element-text').innerHTML = "Measure exposure to ad categories.";
    } else if ( selectedOption == "document-audit") {
        document.getElementById('terms-element-text').innerHTML = "Check if and how terms and conditions are enforced on the platform.";
        document.getElementById('interface-element-text').innerHTML = "Compare to, e.g., Usability ISO guidelines.";
        document.getElementById('data-element-text').innerHTML = "Compare data protection measures to the state of the art.";
        document.getElementById('content-element-text').innerHTML = "Review content moderation guidelines.";
    } else if ( selectedOption == "architecture-audit") {
        document.getElementById('content-element-text').innerHTML = "Evaluate the process of content moderation, what is flagged automatically and what levels of manual review are employed.";
        document.getElementById('report-element-text').innerHTML = "What is the process for handling user reports and how are the outcomes documented.";
    } else if ( selectedOption == "automated-audit") {
        document.getElementById('interface-element-text').innerHTML = "Measure clicks to estimate usage of platform elements.";
        document.getElementById('content-element-text').innerHTML = "Test what content get’s flagged automatically.";
        document.getElementById('logic-element-text').innerHTML = "Scrape recommended content on search function.";
        document.getElementById('advertisement-element-text').innerHTML = "Scrape advertisements to review political ad campaigns.";
    } else if ( selectedOption == "user-survey") {
        document.getElementById('interface-element-text').innerHTML = "Ask about user interface.";
        document.getElementById('experience-element-text').innerHTML = "Evaluate what platform elements are known and used.";
        document.getElementById('report-element-text').innerHTML = "Ask about the experience with reporting mechanisms.";
    } else if ( selectedOption == "user-experience") {
        document.getElementById('crowd-audit-text').innerHTML = "Measure what platform elements users access most often.";
        document.getElementById('survey-audit-text').innerHTML = "Evaluate what platform elements are known and used.";
    } else if ( selectedOption == "user-interface") {
        document.getElementById('document-audit-text').innerHTML = "Compare to, e.g., Usability ISO guidelines.";
        document.getElementById('survey-audit-text').innerHTML = "Ask about user interface.";
        document.getElementById('automated-audit-text').innerHTML = "Measure clicks to estimate usage of platform elements.";
    } else if ( selectedOption == "algorithmic-logic") {
        document.getElementById('code-audit-text').innerHTML = "Review source code, evaluate model parameters.";
        document.getElementById('crowd-audit-text').innerHTML = "Measure exposure to specific (harmful) content.";
        document.getElementById('automated-audit-text').innerHTML = "Scrape recommended content on search function.";
    } else if ( selectedOption == "content-moderation") {
        document.getElementById('document-audit-text').innerHTML = "Review content moderation guidelines.";
        document.getElementById('architecture-audit-text').innerHTML = "Evaluate the process of content moderation, what is flagged automatically and what levels of manual review are employed.";
        document.getElementById('automated-audit-text').innerHTML = "Test what content get’s flagged automatically.";
    } else if ( selectedOption == "terms-conditions") {
        document.getElementById('document-audit-text').innerHTML = "Check if and how terms and conditions are enforced on the platform.";
    } else if ( selectedOption == "advertisement") {
        document.getElementById('crowd-audit-text').innerHTML = "Measure exposure to ad categories.";
        document.getElementById('automated-audit-text').innerHTML = "Scrape advertisements to review political ad campaigns.";
    } else if ( selectedOption == "report-mechanisms") {
        document.getElementById('architecture-audit-text').innerHTML = "What is the process for handling user reports and how are the outcomes documented.";
        document.getElementById('survey-audit-text').innerHTML = "Ask about the experience with reporting mechanisms.";
    } else if ( selectedOption == "data-practices") {
        document.getElementById('code-audit-text').innerHTML = "Check dataflows, ensure that sensitive data like ethnicity is not used as model input.";
        document.getElementById('document-audit-text').innerHTML = "Compare data protection measures to the state of the art.";
    }

    allElements.forEach(el=>el.classList.add('layer-hide'));
    allElements.forEach(el=>el.classList.remove('layer-show'));

    connectedElements.forEach(el=>el.classList.remove('layer-hide'));
    connectedElements.forEach(el=>el.classList.add('layer-show'));
}
</script> 
<center><i>This is an interactive graphic. Use your mouse to explore the process.</i></center>
</div>

<p>While we initially described those 4 steps as consecutive, we learned quite quickly through our RSBA journey that this process needs to be iterative. For example, we recommended deciding on a systemic risk <em>before</em> starting the RSBA process. However, as an independent Civil Society Organisation conducting an external risk assessment, we discovered that certain risks only surfaced during the exploration phase, while others we anticipated were hindered by inaccessibility of data due to imposed restrictions. This realization underscores the intricate interplay between exploration, systemic risk identification, and the selection of appropriate measures. Navigating these steps iteratively becomes imperative to address the challenges inherent in external risk assessment comprehensively.</p>

<h1 id="step-1---plan">Step 1 - Plan</h1>

<p>Step 1 of the RSBA process aims to obtain a deep understanding of the platform under scrutiny and identify stakeholders who should be involved in the audit process.</p>

<h2 id="understanding-the-platform">Understanding the platform</h2>

<p>We have taken some time to understand TikTok as a platform and to plan the audit process as a whole. This phase took us much longer than expected.</p>

<center>
<figure class="justify-content-sm-center">

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2024-01_rsba_timeline.svg-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2024-01_rsba_timeline.svg-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2024-01_rsba_timeline.svg-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/2024-01_rsba_timeline.svg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="50%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture><figcaption class="caption">The rough projectplan for the TikTok RSBA</figcaption>

</figure>
</center>

<p>We spent roughly 9 months exploring and understanding TikTok technically and sociologically by swiping, watching and playing around with different data collection options. We set up some experimental sock puppet accounts, started a scraping test run and tried to figure out how to replicate well-known investigations like that from the <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/tiktok-algorithm-video-investigation-11626877477">Wall Street Journal on depression rabbit holes and mental health</a>. This experimental phase was accompanied by a research sprint, and we have already reached out to relevant stakeholders to discuss systemic risks, TikTok and its inner workings (see below).</p>

<p>Using the RSBA’s questions as a guiding framework, here are some things that we learned:</p>

<h3 id="what-type-of-media-is-the-platform-working-with">What type of media is the platform working with?</h3>

<p>TikTok’s most important content type is short, entertaining video clips, from classic cat content and dance challenges to carpet cleaning videos (if you are interested in the trends of 2023, see <a href="https://newsroom.tiktok.com/en-us/year-on-tiktok-2023">TikTok’s overview</a> - available for different countries). The mobile apps allow users to make, edit and upload these videos. Common and well-known features are a huge variety of <a href="https://effecthouse.tiktok.com/">filters</a>, <a href="https://www.capcut.com/templates">CapCut templates</a> and the possibility to remix videos with <a href="https://www.tiktok.com/music/Love-You-So-6728562975734515713">audio snippets</a> or <a href="https://www.tiktok.com/@thebigguyryback22/video/7107352337106079018">other videos in duets</a>. The videos are posted with additional descriptions and hashtags and can be published with subtitles. Although a duration of up to 10 minutes is possible, the average video is still short (around 35 seconds) because the platform logic favors that.</p>

<p>In recent years, TikTok LIVE has also gained significance for creators and contributed to TikTok’s revenue (see turnover data below). However, the majority of users’ time on the platform is still spent on the For You feed.</p>

<h3 id="what-is-the-audience">What is the audience?</h3>

<p>TikTok is extremely popular among younger users. In a survey that we conducted as part of the RSBA process with young people between 18 and 25 in Germany, 59% stated that they use TikTok (for global statistics, see <a href="https://www.statista.com/statistics/1299771/tiktok-global-user-age-distribution/">here</a>). It has been <a href="https://archive.ph/NzzG6">reported</a> that Gen Z (people born between 1996 and 2010) use the platform as a search engine and <a href="https://reutersinstitute.politics.ox.ac.uk/digital-news-report/2023">others</a> have found that youth are using it as a trustworthy news source. At least in our own research, we cannot confirm the latter. In our survey, 70% said they do not find TikTok trustworthy (they trust YouTube, though). Still, more than half of our surveyed users use TikTok for information search. (Yes, this is a sneak peek into our data. More data and reflections on our methodology will follow. Stay posted.).</p>

<p>As these youth start shaping their understanding of the world through TikTok, the content they engage with and their relationship to the platform has far-reaching consequences for them as individuals but also for societies at large. Many of these consequences include systemic risks that fall under the umbrella of the <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX:32022R2065">DSA</a>.</p>

<h3 id="what-is-the-platforms-main-strategy">What is the platform’s main strategy?</h3>

<p>In an internal document first published in 2021, the platform explains the rationale of TikTok’s recommendation algorithm (you can find the translated version on our GitHub page <a href="https://github.com/snv-berlin/tiktok-audit/blob/main/TikTok%20Algo%20101%20EN.md">TikTok 101</a>). That document describes TikTok’s main goal as increasing the number of daily active users and the time spent on the platform. To reach these objectives, the designers of the recommender system for the For you Page outline a number of “values”:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Create value for the user:</strong> The “user value” is defined by TikTok as a short-term value, implemented in the algorithm, measured in time spent on the platform within a session (”keep them scrolling”), and as a long-term goal to ensure that users come back to the app (retention).</li>
  <li><strong>Value for authors:</strong> Value for creators is defined as traffic to videos, interactions, income, etc., obtained by the creator.</li>
  <li><strong>Platform value:</strong> TikTok generates the platform value through the algorithm based on factors like platform revenue, content security, brand effect and others.</li>
  <li><strong>Indirect value:</strong> This is measured in metrics such as the notifications received by other users after commenting, as this may increase the retention of these users (”the user value of other users”), or the impact on the content ecosystem (”the author value of other authors”) and so on.</li>
</ol>

<p>Just looking at the aforementioned Key Performance Indicators (KPIs), the developers reached their goals. In January 2024, <a href="https://www.data.ai/apps/all-stores/app/1000600000575007/intelligence">TikTok has 15 million active users in Germany with an average watch time of 1h40min</a>.</p>

<p>However, these KPIs are the goals defined for the recommender system. Of course, for the company employing the engineers working on those algorithms, increased usage is not a goal in itself. Bytedance, the company behind TikTok, is a for-profit organization with financial interests. Increasing the number of users and the time spent on TikTok allows Bytedance to steer more users toward the elements of the platform that drive profit.</p>

<p>When it comes to monetization, TikTok relies on various strategies. <a href="https://s3.eu-west-2.amazonaws.com/document-api-images-live.ch.gov.uk/docs/0m7DPgJC0LdUSttGiJaUtFWgUwIh_AK618dJx1huX8I/application-pdf?X-Amz-Algorithm=AWS4-HMAC-SHA256&amp;X-Amz-Credential=ASIAWRGBDBV3KBPSMTWI%2F20240116%2Feu-west-2%2Fs3%2Faws4_request&amp;X-Amz-Date=20240116T183730Z&amp;X-Amz-Expires=60&amp;X-Amz-Security-Token=IQoJb3JpZ2luX2VjEAEaCWV1LXdlc3QtMiJHMEUCIQC2IFVb2eyOlf7PJNzTchMTzwMQv%2BpxUcNtMqAaOqegbwIgNWGZuwzHK9TzPEQonWikLbO0e80VmlHWs%2FzombOMGAcqxAUIqf%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FARAEGgw0NDkyMjkwMzI4MjIiDEWMWS9fnMRHdZ2KkiqYBfYeey1%2FmdDgRZfaDzs2ow4XQfffAPNxK6je%2B9wPEpkZpsf9OjjMJiW%2F2b%2Fck2hkJl%2BxY1yukLJIWgW4UUMGfFh3oZvw9Nyq7aIZ95nKVaLRlTeLgpzVuHdeYk5v7EnaAmb1VWUP4HwqYfH3nK0sOOIa25M7vP20kybAmHUcjP0ZPKmX2etMOEL4aaEZ4De5NrkskqqqPtq%2ByF7UTIBqggj6SoZ6mGZMP%2BcPg9pSluBFqrlNXHF%2BfViEdY47L3T002q7Azqgg5Q0EBXL%2FomTNU2Y%2BSDgDjr7NVGkPy43R1fIDjognebz3IISj94ltg6FMH8ARCcpDiS5qJ6zNiHnvSrGc8CK9%2Bq2xnhr%2B3z2NL7CJvJtWVIBsvPlyC1%2BNfBxpmRQf4q2JpvK1xW4a68grZIpG8IZlguGScE%2Bg8llGRSHrcXdgscUwNwM72KXdV7UuAE%2BrtwFCi654Qj64T30GJksceaAbVLqB37lJabrVsV8KwJtQY4u04T7ffVVqTeNnAAIWm%2B3y0f7MljianOjBmOuA%2FmjfSPm5kEcQdA9PsjrPjr0th3rQ%2FUkyQ1VgjTrbpV5VhK7ipb60zFflgdYXHn5fFuSJsyqAWz4RKYokpaDdYZIEdJRLiUAofS084hUWR1uuTQC6KtlIkXu%2F7FtC48gpuo%2Bjh%2FytLoEwAEc8jMor62eefLZGJF0dEU5wssIyrKMAnC9flGUbkWSBjo9c19Q5bJN7bUdp1cL7ApnriowDHJmFoz2vOrHqGjnT28bEuux12GgQLjKJrFYZ6gwCqpuLLPQHKfALk3MfmkzLRixLaSAKR0nYrla2ls8%2FDdyLiRIP9eEg%2BYOLr9roJ5x67dS1iQ6hjwznuu%2FAdMXUh4exCbvREGd63swyNiarQY6sQGWVxvwISUzdRsb%2FpZa8cVMpj7jLkg7VCIJENdNyw010AsoB5gHUBoKGZ9o6LaeqhEEDQRVfpXu4ma3MgpSTbX4yhVbV%2BQDcuPfZKJw0NdwetbHglNdFfU42x0CS%2BQ5KywsLep24RQtObC0yk7QDo%2F4H8s8JKUPPqLQJzT5%2F10c0Ia%2Fv6V7a5nwyVg%2BDB1M72Vu1wYJr9YLg7pPUcaVzI%2FYuvLB3oulFuu1GidxJ8vMdo8%3D&amp;X-Amz-SignedHeaders=host&amp;response-content-disposition=inline%3Bfilename%3D%22companies_house_document.pdf%22&amp;X-Amz-Signature=6726470d5bde45bdc18800c3045398fd61c0e9949d48bef8cab9ac43296f50a5">An official document from TikTok UK reports a turnover of $2,618,121,000 for 2022 (of which $1,485,861,000 is in the EU).</a> Broken down by segments, at least in 2022, more than 60% of the turnover came from online advertising services, followed by the Livestreaming programme with 30%. Reports from 2023 suggest that this ratio might have changed over the last year. In 2023, TikTok was the first non-game app to reach <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/12/11/tiktok-becomes-first-non-game-app-to-reach-10b-in-consumer-spending/?guccounter=1">10 billion in consumer spending</a> by selling coins to users with which they can tip content creators.</p>

<p>Besides that, TikTok is also expanding its <a href="https://shop.tiktok.com/business/en">shopping functionality</a> (see <a href="https://socialmediawatchblog.de/2023/09/19/wie-gehts-eigentlich-tiktok/">Social Media Watch Blog from 19.09.2023</a>, German Source).</p>

<p>As TikTok is not a publicly traded company, official financial reports with detailed and meaningful data are difficult to find and are only available sporadically. Similar to the algorithms of the recommender system, we can only make assumptions here about how the company works.</p>

<h3 id="what-technical-elements-are-of-interest">What technical elements are of interest?</h3>

<p>As described above, TikTok has different features that might be managed internally by different product teams, meaning they might all behave differently and, therefore, may require separate algorithm audits.</p>

<p>For our RSBA process, we decided to concentrate on two of the platform’s technical elements: the For You feed and the search page.</p>

<p>In case you have never seen the mobile TikTok app at work, here is a short screencast:</p>

<style>
    video{max-height:500px}
</style>

<div class="row justify-content-sm-center"><div class="col-sm-6 mt-6 mt-md-6">


<figure>

  

  <video muted="" controls="" autoplay="" preload="auto">
    <source src="/assets/video/2024-01_TikTok-Quick-Intro.webm" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="50%" height="auto" type="video/webm" />
  </video>

  

</figure>
 
</div></div>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>For You feed:</strong> Regardless of the client the user is employing (Android, iOS, or web), TikTok’s most important product is the “For You” feed, also known within TikTok as #FYP (For You Page). This feature is mentioned in the <a href="https://www.tiktok.com/legal/page/eea/terms-of-service/en">Terms of Service</a> as “a unique TikTok feature”, and when people talk about <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/tiktoks-secret-sauce-poses-challenge-for-u-s-oversight-researchers-say-11675818735">TikTok’s secret sauce</a>, they usually refer to the algorithmic recommender system of this feature. It can be considered TikTok’s homepage and is the page where users spend the majority of their time on. This FYP is based on a recommender system that uses various behavioral metrics (we will elaborate further in an upcoming blog post; for now, see <a href="https://github.com/snv-berlin/tiktok-audit/blob/main/TikTok%20Algo%20101%20EN.md">TikTok 101</a>) to recommend videos for the user to watch. It shows a mixture of video clips, livestreams and ads - all seemingly related to the users’ interests.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Search Page:</strong> If you click on the search icon in the app (see video above), this leads you to TikTok’s search page. This page works with several forms of automated search suggestions, from which we are most interested in the following: <strong>A list of suggestions labeled “you may like”.</strong> Here TikTok suggests several topics you might want to search for. When you click on one of these suggestions, TikTok leads you to another page with search results (see video above).</p>

    <p>Throughout our RSBA process, we discovered that TikTok is reworking this section constantly. In our data, we found evidence that TikTok is running A/B tests, and we observed that the interface and design were constantly changing.</p>

    <p>When we started to approach this functionality, the suggestions in the “you may like” section were marked with red and grey bullet points. Additionally, some suggestions were  labeled with a <strong>🔥</strong> icon. During our data collection phase, this icon was replaced by the 📈 icon. At least on the accounts we were working with.</p>

    <p>While other people refer to the “you may like” section as <a href="https://blog.xeit.ch/tiktok-als-suchmaschine-wie-40-der-jugendlichen-google-den-ruecken-kehren/">“hot topics”</a> or “trending topics”, we have a different stance here. Regardless of the marker, there seem to be three categories of these suggestions:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Some refer to topics related to the recently watched video,</li>
      <li>some seem to be related to current events on the platform,</li>
      <li>and some seem to be related to current events outside of the platform or news headlines<em>.</em></li>
    </ul>

    <p>Little attention has been paid to this functionality and we did not find any descriptions of how it works, neither by TikTok itself nor by external researchers. However, there are clear indications that TikTok is generally working on its search function. Besides the changes we detected during our research, there were press releases announcing the <a href="https://www.tiktok.com/business/en/blog/introducing-tiktok-search-ads-toggle">integration of ads into the search</a> and hints that <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/tiktok-google-test-new-search-partnership-2023-9?op=1">TikTok is experimenting with third-party integrations, including a test run with Google.</a></p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>While the decision to explore the #FYP’s recommender was due to its importance to the user experience, our interest in the “you may like” section was piqued by the irritating, sometimes <a href="https://tiktok-audit.com/blog/2023/Israel-Hamas-War-Suggestions/">clickbaity</a> and sometimes weird search suggestions we found there. We will explain our decisions further in the related upcoming blog posts.</p>

<h2 id="identify-and-reach-out-to-stakeholders">Identify and reach out to stakeholders</h2>

<p>For the RSBA process, we identified 5 stakeholder groups that can potentially be involved.</p>

<center>
<figure class="justify-content-sm-center">

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2024-01_rsba_stakeholder-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2024-01_rsba_stakeholder-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2024-01_rsba_stakeholder-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/2024-01_rsba_stakeholder.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="50%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

</figure>
</center>

<p>For our TikTok Audit endeavor, we decided to engage with all five stakeholder groups throughout the process:</p>

<p><strong>Platforms:</strong> Unsurprisingly, communication with the platform under scrutiny was reserved. Although we reached out several times and took part in some official workshops and webinars provided by TikTok, the platform did not seem interested in any sort of substantial exchange. We got access to the ad library API but have been informed that affiliation with a university or academic institution is required for access to the Research API.</p>

<p><strong>Independent contractors:</strong> In Article 37, the DSA requires external compliance audits for very large online platforms. This can also encompass the auditing of risk assessments carried out internally by the platforms themselves. That is why we considered it to be helpful to involve independent contractors in the assessments and the audits of recommender systems because they bring specific audit expertise from other fields (e.g., finance, due diligence, etc.). Therefore, we reached out to several companies, which we guessed might become independent contractors at some point. During these exchanges, we learned a lot about the compliance audit business. As large auditors officially stated during the <a href="https://dsa-observatory.eu/2023/11/28/dsa-audits-procedural-rules-leave-some-uncertainties/">consultation on the draft delegated act on audits</a>, one of their concerns is that the DSA does not provide clearly established criteria against which to assure. This goes hand in hand with the fear of having to define normative criteria and make <a href="https://dsa-observatory.eu/2023/11/28/dsa-audits-procedural-rules-leave-some-uncertainties/">normative decisions</a>. That is why, in the end, we could not discuss our approach any further due to speaking completely different languages.</p>

<p><strong>Legal experts</strong>: Legal experts were not among the stakeholders we contacted early on in the process. It was only when we started to set up the measurements that we started talking to consumer protection authorities and legal experts. These conversations helped us to reflect on our scenario definitions and the data setup. Beyond that, we learned more about specific harms to consumer protection stemming from platforms like Amazon or <a href="https://tiktok-audit.com/blog/2024/temu-tiktok/">Temu</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Representatives of affected groups:</strong> When we started our RSBA process, we immediately reached out to the alliance of TikTok creators, Toca, but had to learn that it did not exist anymore. We also chatted with creators occasionally in workshops, but when we started to work on the specific risk scenarios, it became clear that our focus should be on all TikTok users of a younger age group. Therefore, the “affected group” under scrutiny became “TikTok users between the ages of 18 and 25”.</p>

<p><strong>Users:</strong> Our main goal then was to learn as much as possible about the TikTok user group under 25. To make that possible and set up a proper and structured engagement process that goes beyond anecdotal evidence, we decided on doing focus groups. These focus groups have helped us understand the user journey and learn more about the risks that TikTok users themselves perceive on the platform. Our most important finding here was how much the younger generation is concerned about how content and advertisements on TikTok negatively influence the users’ self-image. Therefore, we decided to develop one risk scenario on that specific topic.</p>

<p><strong>Researchers:</strong> Since we wanted to have the users’ perspective integrated into our risk assessment and also focus on societal implications, we decided to work together with a specialized research institute. Our partner for the aforementioned focus groups as well as the survey part of our RSBA process, was <a href="https://pollytix.de">pollytix</a>, a research company experienced in social and political sciences.</p>

<p><strong>Civil Society Researchers:</strong> Although in theory, CSO and researchers are separate stakeholder groups, we noticed a large overlap in our stakeholder engagement. Besides journalistic investigations, it was primarily other <a href="https://www.amnesty.org/en/documents/POL40/7349/2023/en/">civil</a> <a href="https://www.isdglobal.org/digital_dispatches/it-is-still-shockingly-easy-to-find-terrorist-content-on-tiktok/">society</a> <a href="https://foundation.mozilla.org/de/campaigns/strategies-for-studying-tiktok-during-the-german-election/">organizations</a> <a href="https://aiforensics.org/work/tiktok-mobile-vs-web">that</a> had also begun to examine TikTok closely and were open to exchanging knowledge and experience respectively. Therefore, we reflected on every step of our journey with different CSOs, their researchers and computer and data scientists. In the end, we decided to work together with AI Forensics, an organization experienced in adversarial audits of recommender systems.</p>

<p><strong>Together with <a href="https://aiforensics.org/">AI Forensics</a> and <a href="https://pollytix.eu/">pollytix</a>, we developed the scenarios and opted for specific data collection methods (see following blog posts on Steps 2 and 3 coming soon).</strong></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="rsba" /><category term="methodology," /><category term="process," /><category term="step1" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A short analysis of political ads and TikToks new advertisement library]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">🛍️ Shop Till You Drop…: How Temu exploits TikTok’s affordances</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/temu-tiktok/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="🛍️ Shop Till You Drop…: How Temu exploits TikTok’s affordances" /><published>2024-01-10T13:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-01-10T13:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/temu-tiktok</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/temu-tiktok/"><![CDATA[<div class="row justify-content-sm-center"><div class="col-sm-6 mt-6 mt-md-6">
<center>
<figure class="justify-content-sm-center">

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2024-01_tt-temu-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2024-01_tt-temu-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2024-01_tt-temu-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/2024-01_tt-temu.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" alt="generated with DALL·E 3" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

</figure>
</center> 
</div></div>

<p><em>By <a href="https://www.stiftung-nv.de/en/person/alexander-hohlfeld">Alexander Hohlfeld</a> and <a href="https://www.stiftung-nv.de/en/person/dr-anna-katharina-messmer">Kathy Meßmer</a></em></p>

<p>With over 50 million active users and more than 3 million downloads <a href="https://www.data.ai/de/apps/ios/app/temu-team-up-price-down/?MEANINGFUL_INTERACTION_COUNT=3&amp;mps_date_filter=30-days">in the weeks before Christmas</a>, the app “Temu” is dominating both the Google Play and the App Store charts.</p>

<p>Temu was founded in July 2022 as a subsidiary of the Chinese company “PDD Holdings”, only a few months after PDD Holdings´ shopping app <a href="https://www.reuters.com/technology/google-suspends-chinas-pinduoduo-app-due-malware-issues-2023-03-21/">“Pinduoduo” was suspended from Google’s Play store</a> due to security concerns and malware issues. The app faced <a href="https://edition.cnn.com/2023/04/02/tech/china-pinduoduo-malware-cybersecurity-analysis-intl-hnk/index.html">drastic accusations from researchers</a>. It might continuously run in the background, preventing itself from being uninstalled and thereby pushing its monthly user base. It might have the ability to spy on tracking activities of competing shopping apps or even the social network accounts of users.</p>

<p>The rebranding as “Temu” for Western countries and the <a href="https://www.dw.com/en/temu-app-downloads-soar-as-western-shoppers-look-for-cheap-chinese-goods-and-sales/a-66683429">relocation of its office</a> for the European market to Dublin can be interpreted as attempts to distract from the scandals of its mother company. However, this should not obscure the fact that Temu is also struggling with serious consumer protection problems.</p>

<p>First of all, <a href="https://www.politico.eu/article/booming-chinese-shopping-app-temu-faces-western-scrutiny-over-data-security-2/">similar data privacy concerns</a> have already been expressed about the Temu app as with the earlier Pinduoduo app.</p>

<p>Second, Temu considers itself not an online shop but rather an “online marketplace”, even though that is barely visible to the user. In a <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20231004112508/https:/www.temu.com/de/terms-of-use.html">previous version of its Terms of Use from August 29th</a>, Temu used that position to distance itself from the products it sold and denied any liability:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“We do not have control over and do not guarantee the existence, quality, safety, suitability, or legality of the Products or the truthfulness, accuracy or legality of any information contained in the Product listings or other information provided by Sellers or other users”.</p>

</blockquote>

<p>In the <a href="https://www.temu.com/de/terms-of-use.html">latest version of the Terms of Use</a> from December 29th, this has been updated and Temu admits its liability “<strong>for slight negligent breach of essential obligations</strong>”. What this means in practice still needs to be investigated.</p>

<p>Third, products on Temu are extremely cheap and it can be assumed that this goes hand in hand with low quality and a lack of consumer protection standards. Many products offered on Temu have astonishing optical similarities with products of famous brands, thus moving on the border being considered as counterfeit products.</p>

<p>Finally, Temu is working with highly deceptive design practices. There are indications that some of these could be considered as misleading practices under European competition law. According to the <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?qid=1410437777196&amp;uri=CELEX:32005L0029">EU Directive on Unfair Commercial Practices</a> a practice shall be regarded as misleading if the practice is “like to receive the average consumer” and is “likely to cause [..] a transactional decision that he [the customer] would not have taken otherwise”. This includes, for example <a href="https://europa.eu/youreurope/citizens/consumers/unfair-treatment/unfair-commercial-practices/index_en.htm">“phony ‘free’ offers”, “dark design patterns”, such as “fake countdowns”, “false offers of prizes, gifts” or “false use of limited offers”</a>.</p>

<div class="row justify-content-sm-center"><div class="col-sm-6 mt-6 mt-md-6">
<center>
<figure class="justify-content-sm-center">

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2024-01_temu_pricewheel-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2024-01_temu_pricewheel-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2024-01_temu_pricewheel-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/2024-01_temu_pricewheel.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="50%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

</figure>
</center> 
</div></div>
<p><em>Screenshot of a price wheel on temu</em></p>

<p>Temu is promoting price wheels all throughout the app, which usually offer supposedly “free” products. At first glance, it is not obvious to the user that the products advertised as “free” are in fact not free at all. The user needs to order a certain amount of other products to be able to proceed with the order. The “price wheels” also do not seem to work randomly, but in fact propose that the user would get the “Jackpot” almost all the time. A constant flood of notifications on allegedly free products or prizes is pressuring the user and creating “FOMO” (fear of missing out). Until recently, a countdown in the upper left corner offered “Free Shipping”  and restarted as soon as the countdown ended. But this might just be one example of fake limited offers on Temu. Opening the website or the app reveals an avalanche of countdowns and supposedly time-limited offers. While a more detailed legal investigation would be desirable, it seems obvious that these practices can have deceptive effects.</p>

<p>As a reader of our blog – that is about auditing TikTok – you might wonder: <strong><em>What does this have to do with TikTok</em>?</strong> We argue that the success of Temu is, to a large extent, built on the platform affordances of TikTok. No app or product has ever exploited the platforms’ logic this systematically before.</p>

<center>
<figure class="justify-content-sm-center">

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2024-01_tt_temu_hashtag_use-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2024-01_tt_temu_hashtag_use-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2024-01_tt_temu_hashtag_use-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/2024-01_tt_temu_hashtag_use.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

</figure>
</center>

<p><em>The screenshot above is from <a href="https://ads.tiktok.com/business/creativecenter/hashtag/temu?period=365&amp;countryCode=DE">TikToks Trend Analysis site for marketers</a> and shows that the #temu hashtag was used more than 53.000 times last year in Germany alone. For comparison, the hashtag #amazon was used 50.000 times in that time.</em></p>

<p>Temu is extremely present on TikTok. Videos with the hashtag “<strong>temu</strong>” generated a total of <strong>9.9B</strong> <strong>views</strong>, <strong>#temuhaul</strong> a total of <strong>3.4B</strong> <strong>views</strong> and <strong>#temufinds</strong> <strong>2.5B views</strong> (09.01.2024). What makes Temu so successful on TikTok is that they perfectly understood the platform and developed strategies to exploit its platform logic. Their strategy builds on three main pillars:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Influencer Program</li>
  <li>Affiliate Program</li>
  <li>Gamification efforts</li>
</ol>

<p><strong>The Influencer Program:</strong> Temu is trying to <a href="https://www.temu.com/influencer-collaboration.html">recruit influencers</a> with a mix of free products and monthly “influencer cash”. The key to its strategy is not to focus on specific or famous influencers. Instead, everyone with more than 300 followers can register for their program. That strategy makes it possible to <strong>flood TikTok with the content of so-called “Nano-influencers”</strong>. Temu proudly claims that “10,000+ influencers have already collaborated with Temu”. At the same time, the influencer program uses gamification strategies. Influencers are encouraged to “join campaigns”, “post and share” and thereby earn “benefits” (mainly Temu vouchers).</p>

<p><strong>The Affiliate Program:</strong> The so-called “<a href="https://www.temu.com/affiliate_account_activity.html">Affiliate Program</a>” takes this strategy to another level. To join, a user does not even need to have 300 followers. Everyone can create affiliate codes which are then shared on <strong>TikTok</strong> to receive a commission. This leads to a flood of spam content and comments from people promoting their affiliate codes. The registration is quite simple; all it takes is a Temu and a social media account (Instagram, TikTok or YouTube). With notifications like “xx earned 2.817,59€”, a starting balance of “3€” and statistics that are framed as games (such as “Ranking Race” or “Referral Race”), the users are encouraged to share their codes and referral links. Temu specifically encourages users to share them “in your bio”, “in your post” or “Send to your friends”. The promises of quick money (2€ reward for each download through the referral link) and large sums (e.g., 5,000€ bonus) are especially tempting for young people, leading them to spam social media network sites such as TikTok with their affiliate codes.</p>

<div class="row justify-content-sm-center"><div class="col-sm-6 mt-6 mt-md-6">
<center>
<figure class="justify-content-sm-center">

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2024-01_temu_affiliate_program-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2024-01_temu_affiliate_program-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2024-01_temu_affiliate_program-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/2024-01_temu_affiliate_program.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="50%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

</figure>
</center> 
</div></div>
<p><em>Screenshot of the affiliate program screen in the Temu app</em></p>

<p>Although Temu (hidden under “more details”) points out that, “[u]nauthorized commission obtained through false advertising or posting referral codes as irrelevant comments on any videos or app stores is prohibited”, we were able to find a large number of such comments on <strong>TikTok</strong>.</p>

<p><strong>Gamification Efforts:</strong> Temu is also offering different gambling-like <a href="https://www.temu.com/de/games.html">mini games</a>, creating group pressure, to which young people are particularly susceptible:</p>

<ul>
  <li>“Temu Fishland Game is an underwater adventure that allows players to catch fish and earn money based on the size and rarity of their catch.”</li>
  <li>“Temu Farmland is a farming simulation game where players can grow crops, raise animals, and sell their produce for a profit.”</li>
  <li>“Temu Redeem Cash is a game that offers users the chance to win real money by redeeming coins earned through other Temu games.”</li>
  <li>“Temu Lucky Flip is a game of chance where players can win big by flipping a coin and guessing the outcome correctly.”</li>
  <li>“Temu Free Gift is a daily bonus game that rewards users with free coins and prizes just for logging in.”</li>
</ul>

<p>While constantly pushing the user to new price wheels for allegedly “free products”, encouraging users to share codes and links as well as strong gamification efforts, the combination of Temu with social media platforms like TikTok might cause consumer protection harms that need further investigation. We are currently investigating these harms, that result from the exploitation of TikTok´s affordances by e-commerce platforms like Temu or “fast fashion” apps like “Shein”. Follow our blog to not miss our next articles.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="rsba" /><category term="analysis," /><category term="temu," /><category term="fyp," /><category term="tiktokmademebuyit" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A short analysis of political ads and TikToks new advertisement library]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">🍽️ Minors à la carte: TikTok allows profiling of underage teens</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/Minors-a-la-carte-TikTok-allows-profiling-of-underage-teens/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="🍽️ Minors à la carte: TikTok allows profiling of underage teens" /><published>2023-11-07T11:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-11-07T11:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/Minors-a-la-carte-TikTok-allows-profiling-of-underage-teens</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/Minors-a-la-carte-TikTok-allows-profiling-of-underage-teens/"><![CDATA[<p>*By: <a href="https://www.stiftung-nv.de/en/person/santiago-sordo-ruz">Santiago Sordo Ruz</a>, <a href="https://www.stiftung-nv.de/de/person/anna-semenova">Anna Semenova</a> and <a href="https://www.stiftung-nv.de/en/person/dr-martin-degeling">Martin Degeling</a>.</p>

<p>In <a href="https://tiktok-audit.com/blog/2023/ads-targeting-minors/">a previous post</a>, we shared that TikTok is still allowing advertisers to target minors -aged between 13 and 17- despite announcing that it would stop this practice starting 11 July. Today we dive a little deeper into this topic to discuss the subtleties of the role that profiling plays in advertising to this particularly vulnerable age group and the platform’s compliance with its own announcement and the DSA. After an explanation of what profiling means in the context of the DSA, we show that despite some recent changes regarding this practice, TikTok is neither completely adhering to their own standards, nor to the DSA.</p>

<h2 id="profiling-in-targeted-advertising">Profiling in targeted advertising</h2>

<p>To maximise the impact of their campaigns, advertisers seek to serve content that is as close to tailor-made to their target audiences as possible. User <strong>profiling</strong> enables by estimating the interests of individual user and is standard practice in the online marketing industry. However, abiding by the DSA’s online protection of minors provisions, which will be applicable across the EU from 17 February 2024, entails refraining from targeting advertisements to minors by profiling them. Article 28(2) reads:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Providers of online platform [<strong><em>sic</em></strong>] shall not present advertisements on their interface <strong>based on</strong> <strong>profiling</strong> as defined [<a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX%3A32016R0679&amp;qid=1697727163779#d1e1489-1-1">in the GDPR</a>] using personal data of the recipient of the service when they are aware with reasonable certainty that the recipient of the service is a minor.</p>

</blockquote>

<p>The <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX%3A32016R0679&amp;qid=1697727163779#d1e1489-1-1">definition</a> in the GDPR is the following:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>‘profiling’ means any form of automated processing of personal data consisting of the use of personal data to evaluate certain personal aspects relating to a natural person, in particular to analyse or predict aspects concerning that natural person’s performance at work, economic situation, health, personal preferences, interests, reliability, behaviour, location or movements;</p>

</blockquote>

<p>So, with these definitions in mind, is TikTok enabling profiling to target minors with ads?</p>

<h2 id="the-profiling-menu">The profiling menu</h2>

<p>To answer this question, let’s first look more closely into <a href="https://library.tiktok.com/ads">TikTok’s Ad Library</a>. The data we have gathered from it includes an interesting set of variables that is literally prefixed with the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">targeting</code> keyword. While we can’t know this for certain, we have every reason to believe these variables describe some of the characteristics that the DSA is trying to protect: personal preferences, interests and behaviour.</p>

<p>To investigate our question, we looked at the data we have collected for Germany and filtered for ads presented to minors which also used at least one of these variables: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">targeting.audience</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">targeting.interest</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">targeting.video_interactions</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">targeting.creator_interactions</code>. If you hover over the ⓘ symbol beside a variable on any ad in the library, the following descriptions pop-up:</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Variable</th>
      <th>Description</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>audience</td>
      <td>Whether the ad was shown to users who belong to or share similar characteristics to a specific audience list. These lists are based on the users’ on and off-TikTok activity as specified by the advertiser.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>interest</td>
      <td>Whether the ad was shown to users in these interest categories.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>video_interactions</td>
      <td>This ad was shown to users who engaged with videos in these categories.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>creator_interactions</td>
      <td>This ad was shown to users who followed or viewed creators in these categories.</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>It would be very interesting to have a closer look into the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">audience</code> variable to see how those audience lists look like and -especially- to figure out what kind of off-TikTok activity it considers, but we won’t do it here. Let’s illustrate what the other three variables describe and how they enable profiling. Consider the following table, which ranks the most popular targeting categories in our data:</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Rank</th>
      <th>interest</th>
      <th>creator_interactions</th>
      <th>video_interactions</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>Beauty &amp; personal care</td>
      <td>Fashion &amp; beauty</td>
      <td>Beauty &amp; style</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>2</td>
      <td>Apparel &amp; accessories</td>
      <td>Game</td>
      <td>Entertainments</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>3</td>
      <td>Games</td>
      <td>Relationship</td>
      <td>Lifestyle</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>4</td>
      <td>News &amp; entertainment</td>
      <td>Talent</td>
      <td>Sports &amp; outdoors</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>5</td>
      <td>Life services</td>
      <td>Fashion &amp; beauty, random shoot</td>
      <td>Lifestyle, beauty &amp; style</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>This is a snapshot of the most widely used categories used within the profiling menu that advertisers are offered by the platform to create segments matching their target audiences. If minors are part of this menu, then the company is not only not complying with its own deadline, but also not using profiling to target them <strong>precisely</strong> in the way described in the DSA.</p>

<h2 id="our-findings-and-some-conclusions">Our findings and some conclusions</h2>

<p>The figure below shows how the frequency of ads that target minors <em>and</em> use profiling has evolved in the last months; the red vertical line marks 11 July. As you can see, the platform has been allowing this practice and has continued to do so well past its self-imposed deadline. However, it is also clear that the practice is being discontinued, with some days even exhibiting zero ads. This could mean TikTok is enforcing its decision gradually or that advertisers are aware of the new rules and simply to do attempt to target minors to the same extent.</p>

<div class="row justify-content-sm-center"><div class="col-sm-8 mt-4 mt-md-0">
<center>
<figure class="justify-content-sm-center">

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-11_tt-ads-targeting-minors-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-11_tt-ads-targeting-minors-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-11_tt-ads-targeting-minors-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/2023-11_tt-ads-targeting-minors.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

</figure>
</center> 
</div></div>
<p><em>Image: The number of variables available on TikTok through different means of data acccess.</em></p>

<p>While the real test with respect to the DSA comes on 17 February 2024 when targeting of minors using profiling becomes mandatory we can -for now- qualify our previous finding: TikTok has and is still targeting minors <strong>**</strong><strong>**</strong><strong>**</strong><em>and it has and is still allowing the use of profiling to do so</em><strong>**</strong><strong>**</strong><strong>**</strong>. Even if we see a drop in the numbers, the platform still allows around one 700 ads violating it’s policies and the DSA in September 2023.</p>

<p>What is already clear is that societal oversight -be it on behalf of the government or civil society- is crucial in assuring that the systemic risks associated with Tiktok, other VLOPs and online services in general are mitigated. The technologies and strategies these companies employ are in constant evolution, and we can’t afford to stay behind.</p>

<p>One fundamental ingredient of this oversight is transparency on behalf of platforms. Regulations such as the DSA already constitute important progress in this direction. Tools like Tiktok’s Ad Library and its Research API are important steps towards achieving it. However, we have already seen that such efforts currently <a href="https://tiktok-audit.com/blog/2023/the-TikTok-research-API-falls-woefully-short/">fall woefully short</a>. Be it protecting minors or mitigating any other potential harms, if we want to provide society and governments with tools that actually match the challenge, we must demand broader, deeper and less restricted access to the kind of data that made this post possible.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="ad-library" /><category term="ads," /><category term="analysis" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We look into the Research API and its shortcomings.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">🤦‍♀️ The Research API falls woefully short</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/the-TikTok-research-API-falls-woefully-short/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="🤦‍♀️ The Research API falls woefully short" /><published>2023-10-16T12:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-10-16T12:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/the-TikTok-research-API-falls-woefully-short</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/the-TikTok-research-API-falls-woefully-short/"><![CDATA[<p>*By: <a href="https://www.stiftung-nv.de/en/person/santiago-sordo-ruz">Santiago Sordo Ruz</a>, <a href="https://www.stiftung-nv.de/en/person/dr-martin-degeling">Martin Degeling</a> and <a href="https://www.stiftung-nv.de/en/person/dr-anna-katharina-messmer">Kathy Meßmer</a></p>

<p>TikTok’s reach is measured in the billions. According to different <a href="https://www.usesignhouse.com/blog/tiktok-stats">sources</a>, in 2022 it had 1.7 billion users, 1 billion daily views and 1.12 billion monthly active users. This is why we need a systematic way of accessing data about the platform to conduct thorough research about it - may it be for exploring the platform’s affordances or conducting a full-blown audit.</p>

<p>One way TikTok provides access to some of its data is the Research API. It makes getting some insights into the platform’s inner workings possible, but it is far from satisfactory. Especially because the provided data is very limited compared to which data is publicly available via scraping. So, let’s have a closer look at that.</p>

<div class="row justify-content-sm-center"><div class="col-sm-8 mt-4 mt-md-0">
<center>
<figure class="justify-content-sm-center">

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10_tt-apis-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10_tt-apis-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10_tt-apis-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/2023-10_tt-apis.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

</figure>
</center> 
</div></div>
<p><em>Image: The number of variables available on TikTok through different means of data acccess.</em></p>

<h2 id="tiktoks-research-api">TikTok’s Research API</h2>

<p>TikTok offers an application programming interface (API) where vetted academic researchers can obtain information about the content published by TikTok’s users. An API is —in short— a way to request and obtain information from a system. <a href="https://developers.tiktok.com/products/research-api/">TikTok’s Research API</a> provides access to what is essentially a carefully curated database of the videos the platform hosts.</p>

<p>The API provides data and metadata about comments, users and videos. The number of variables available for each of these categories is as follows:</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Object</th>
      <th>Variables</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Comments</td>
      <td>6</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Users</td>
      <td>8</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Videos</td>
      <td>9</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>These variables contain information about different aspects of the objects in question. For example, this is what is available in the case of comments:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Create Time:</strong> This is the time when the comment was posted on a video.</li>
  <li><strong>ID:</strong> This is the unique comment ID for a comment posted on a video.</li>
  <li><strong>Like Count:</strong> The total number of likes for a comment under a video created by users by clicking the “Heart” icon.</li>
  <li><strong>Parent Comment ID:</strong> This is the unique ID of the parent comment when the user responds to another user’s comment. If the comment was directly entered for a video, this ID is the same as the Video ID.</li>
  <li><strong>Text:</strong> This is the actual text of the comment entered on a video. To protect the privacy of users, other information is removed.</li>
  <li><strong>Video_ID:</strong> This is the video ID for which the comment was entered.</li>
</ol>

<p>The API’s <a href="https://developers.tiktok.com/doc/research-api-codebook">official</a> codebook provides a detailed description of all available variables. While these may shed light on <em>some</em> research questions, especially related to the analysis of content posted on the platform, they are extremely limited in number and scope.</p>

<h2 id="getting-more-useful-data-is-hard">Getting more useful data is hard</h2>

<p>Since civil society organisations like the SNV can’t use the Research API, we decided to explore the platform on our own. We have done this using what is known as content <em>scraping</em>, which is the automated collection of data from online sources. We have collected data from two of TikTok’s clients: the Android app and the web app.</p>

<p>Scraping data from the web is quite common and poses a relatively low technical barrier. However, scraping data from a smartphone app such as TikTok’s Android client is quite challenging; we speak from experience. At the same time, scraping TikTok content from the Android app has proven invaluable. Its smartphone apps are the most natural way to use the platform —providing data closer to what users actually encounter— and <strong>the amount and variety of the information we have collected is incomparable to what is available through the Research API.</strong></p>

<h2 id="the-research-api-falls-woefully-short">The Research API falls woefully short</h2>

<p>Scraping TikTok directly from the source has allowed us to collect information on various platform aspects. We have gained more and better perspectives on comments, users and videos, and also into officially undocumented features like the app’s automated search suggestions.</p>

<p>To illustrate this, let’s have a look at the data and compare the number of variables on which we have collected information through scraping with those offered by the Research API:</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Source</th>
      <th>Variables</th>
      <th>Date collected</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="https://github.com/snv-berlin/tiktok-audit/blob/main/Data%20Access/tiktok_researchapi_annotated_metadata_list.csv">Research API</a></td>
      <td>32</td>
      <td>July 6, 2023</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="https://github.com/snv-berlin/tiktok-audit/blob/main/Data%20Access/tiktok_web_annotated_metadata_list.csv">Web</a></td>
      <td>186</td>
      <td>July 6, 2023</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="https://github.com/snv-berlin/tiktok-audit/blob/main/Data%20Access/tiktok_app_annotated_metadata_list.csv">Android App</a></td>
      <td>845</td>
      <td>July 6, 2023</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>You can have a look at each source’s codebook by clicking on the links in the table; note the trove of insights that scraping affords. Note as well that our codebooks are —and will remain— works in progress.</p>

<p><strong>As you can see, the Research API falls woefully short.</strong> Furthermore, keep in mind that documenting scraped data constitutes a technical challenge, meaning these numbers are conservative estimates.</p>

<h2 id="why-this-matters">Why this matters</h2>

<p><a href="https://developers.tiktok.com/products/research-api/">According to the company</a>, the Research API serves the following purpose:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>TikTok supports independent research about our platform. Through our Research API, academic researchers from non-profit universities in the U.S. and Europe can apply to study public data about TikTok content and accounts.</p>

</blockquote>

<p>Put into perspective, what TikTok offers is such a weak attempt at supporting independent research that one has to ask whether the company is simply <a href="https://www.gmfus.org/news/ai-audit-washing-and-accountability">claiming credit without doing the work</a>. To make things worse, as mentioned above, access is so restricted that our very own researchers at Stiftung Neue Verantwortung do not qualify for the API. Put simply, if we want to be able to scrutinise a platform like TikTok and thus assess the potential harms and impacts that its widespread usage entails, the Research API is grossly inadequate as a window into it.</p>

<p>Ultimately, with some technical expertise, much more data is already publicly available and accessible anyway. It shouldn’t take an in-house computer scientist with a PhD to obtain valuable insights into a social media platform billions of people use. While it is reasonable for the platform to want to keep its inner workings secret, its potential impacts warrant profoundly wider and deeper access to the data generated by its users and about its users. That’s why the data we have obtained should not remain hidden behind a formidable technical wall. On the contrary, it should be made readily available to researchers, including those working within civil society organisations.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="research" /><category term="API" /><category term="analysis" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We look into the Research API and its shortcomings.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">🪖 How TikTok drags users into the digital war zone</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/Israel-Hamas-War-Suggestions/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="🪖 How TikTok drags users into the digital war zone" /><published>2023-10-13T12:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-10-13T12:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/Israel-Hamas-War-Suggestions</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/Israel-Hamas-War-Suggestions/"><![CDATA[<p>*By: <a href="https://www.stiftung-nv.de/en/person/dr-anna-katharina-messmer">Kathy Meßmer</a> and <a href="https://www.stiftung-nv.de/en/person/dr-martin-degeling">Martin Degeling</a></p>

<p>During the ongoing war between Israel and Hamas, social media users opening their feeds experience a melange of true and false information, state and terrorist propaganda, real and fake war footage, news and opinions. This mixture often contains extremely violent and disturbing content.</p>

<p>As different <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2023/10/11/tiktok-youtube-israel-hamas-content-moderation/">news</a> <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/newsletters/2023-10-10/tiktok-videos-of-israel-palestine-conflict-show-new-role-for-the-platform">outlets</a> already <a href="https://www.tagesschau.de/faktenfinder/israel-hamas-fakes-100.html">described</a> with regards to this violent conflict, various actors weaponize social media, including TikTok - quite similar to what we already know from other wars, such as the most recent one in Ukraine. That is why <a href="https://edition.cnn.com/2023/10/12/tech/eu-tiktok-israel-hamas-disinformation/index.html">European Commissioner Thierry Breton warned TikTok</a> - and other platforms - to follow EU rules on dealing with illegal content. Failure to comply could result in penalties.</p>

<p>Indeed, TikTok plays a crucial role in recommending war content to users, also in Germany. However, <strong>our preliminary research suggests it’s not (only) in the way that people usually think of TikTok</strong> - as an algorithmic juggernaut based on tracking users’ viewing preferences. It’s actually a bit messier than that.</p>

<h2 id="you-may-like-on-tiktok">“You may like” on TikTok</h2>

<p>In the reporting on the latest escalation, outlets like the <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2023/10/11/tiktok-youtube-israel-hamas-content-moderation/">Washington Post</a> refer to TikTok’s search suggestions on the search page as “trending searches” to demonstrate the topic’s relevance to users. But we have a different interpretation here because our research suggests that the search strings TikTok recommends to you might not necessarily be trending topics.</p>

<p>At SNV, we have been studying TikTok for several months now, and one feature caught our eye: the suggestions on what to search for. If you open the search page of TikTok (by clicking on the 🔎 icon), you not only get to see your previous search results but there is also a section called “You may like”. This section always contains ten search strings, three of which are usually highlighted by a 🔥 icon.</p>

<div class="row justify-content-sm-center"><div class="col-sm-5 mt-4 mt-md-0">
<center>
<figure class="justify-content-sm-center">

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10_tt_hamas-vs-israel-translated-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10_tt_hamas-vs-israel-translated-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10_tt_hamas-vs-israel-translated-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/2023-10_tt_hamas-vs-israel-translated.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

</figure>
</center> 
</div></div>

<p><em>“You may like”, as shown to a German user on October 13, 2023. Personalized search suggestions were deactivated for this. Yellow boxes show the translated search terms.</em></p>

<p>What struck us the most over the last weeks is how irritating and badly curated these suggestions are. For example, they often refer to strings like “so-and-so died”, suggesting the death of a celebrity, who is, in fact, alive.</p>

<div class="row justify-content-sm-center"><div class="col-sm-5 mt-4 mt-md-1">
<center>
<figure class="justify-content-sm-center">

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10_tt-search-suggestions-chika-died-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10_tt-search-suggestions-chika-died-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10_tt-search-suggestions-chika-died-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/2023-10_tt-search-suggestions-chika-died.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

</figure>
</center> 
</div></div>

<p><em>“You may like” suggested search as shown on October 10, 2023, suggesting that Chika, the rapper, has died. Yet, she seems to be in ok-ish health.</em></p>

<p>Also, these search suggestions come up with random topics, which were sometimes in the news days ago but don’t seem interesting to TikTok users.</p>

<div class="row justify-content-sm-center"><div class="col-sm-4 mt-3 mt-md-0">
<center>
<figure class="justify-content-sm-center">

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10_tt-suggestions_neapolitano-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10_tt-suggestions_neapolitano-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10_tt-suggestions_neapolitano-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/2023-10_tt-suggestions_neapolitano.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

</figure>
</center> 
</div></div>

<p><em>“You may like” suggested search as shown on September 28, 2023, suggesting that Italy’s former president had died. This was actually true for a change, but he had already died one week earlier on the September 22 and his death was not a “trending topic” at the time anymore.</em></p>

<div class="row justify-content-sm-center"><div class="col-sm-4 mt-3 mt-md-0">
<center>
<figure class="justify-content-sm-center">

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10_tt-suggestion-VKI-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10_tt-suggestion-VKI-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10_tt-suggestion-VKI-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/2023-10_tt-suggestion-VKI.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

</figure>
</center> 
</div></div>

<p><em>“You may like” suggested search as shown on September 5, 2023, which covers the funding of the Austrian consumer protection non-profit “Verein für Konsumenteninformation” (VKI). It was not a topic of debate in German news and didn’t strike us as something of importance for many TikTok users.</em></p>

<p>Oftentimes, when you click on these search suggestions and are directed to the results page, you will not find any related videos. For example, in this case, where the suggested search term referenced a very specific event in Austrian news, no video was available on the results page.</p>

<p>In contrast to TikTok’s For You Page, especially the 🔥 recommendations are less personalized. All of this brings us to the <strong>hypothesis that the recommender system of the Search Page is based not solely on what happens <em>on</em> the platform but considers external data, for instance, news headlines.</strong> And it is poorly curated.</p>

<p>Why is this important? As long as the search suggestions are “Kotzhügel” (”Puke Hill”) or “Oktoberfest” - as it was during and after the Octoberfest season in Munich - this may be irritating and entertaining, but nothing to worry about.</p>

<p>This is a different story if search suggestions are replaced with much more violent and potentially traumatizing content. And that’s exactly what happened, as the following lists of the “You may like” suggestions show.</p>

<h2 id="you-may-like-war">You May Like War</h2>

<p>On October 3, 2023, we checked the suggested search topics around 40 times, and the top 10 suggested search terms we found in Germany were as follows:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Rosie Oktoberfest</li>
  <li>Oktoberfest Kotzhügel</li>
  <li>Julienco Ayliva</li>
  <li>Chibi Doll Girl Outfit</li>
  <li>Van Gogh Pokemon</li>
  <li>Kaan Yavi Ex Frau</li>
  <li>Mexify Mutter Tot Hamed</li>
  <li>Köln Marathon 2023</li>
  <li>Frankfurt Verliert 0:2 In Wolfsburg</li>
  <li>From Satan Ist To Islam</li>
</ol>

<p>On October 7, 2023, the day of the attack on Israel, the top 10 “You may like” suggestions were as follows:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Italien Bus Unfall</li>
  <li><strong>Israel Angriff Heute</strong></li>
  <li>I<strong>srael Angriff Heute Live</strong></li>
  <li><strong>Israel Gaza Heute</strong></li>
  <li><strong>Israel Heute Live</strong></li>
  <li>Putin Geburtstag 2023</li>
  <li><strong>Israel October 2023</strong></li>
  <li>Murcia Spain Fire</li>
  <li>Osnabrück Düsseldorf</li>
  <li><strong>Palestina Israel</strong></li>
</ol>

<p>Since then, search suggestions mentioning Israel, Gaza or Palestine are part of the “You may like” section on a daily basis. Furthermore, these more broad search suggestions are accompanied by ones like “Shani Louk Full Video”, referring to the German missing person Shani Louk, who was kidnapped by Hamas during a music festival. <a href="https://edition.cnn.com/2023/10/07/middleeast/israel-gaza-fighting-hamas-attack-music-festival-intl-hnk/index.html">Videos</a> of her dancing and footage of her lying unconscious on a pickup truck went viral.</p>

<center>
<figure class="justify-content-sm-center">

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10_tt-topics_octoberfest_isreal-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10_tt-topics_octoberfest_isreal-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-10_tt-topics_octoberfest_isreal-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/2023-10_tt-topics_octoberfest_isreal.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

</figure>
</center>

<p><em>Image: The plot shows the percentage of “You may like” lists per day containing at least one of the topics. Oktoberfest ended on October 3 and had been frequently suggested before. The most recent conflict between Israel and Hamas has been on every suggested list since the initial terror attacks on October 7.</em></p>

<h2 id="why-the-you-may-like-section-is-problematic">Why the “You may like” Section is Problematic</h2>

<p>With our understanding mentioned above, the “you may like” section seems to be automatically compiled by TikTok, at least partly without connection to users’ behavior or interests. But if the suggestions are not due to individual platform-user interaction, it cannot be argued that users get to see what interests them. Rather, regardless of their interests, TikTok users are dragged into the melange of true and false information as well as war propaganda by TikTok.</p>

<p>This might not be illegal but it is dangerous on several levels:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Search suggestions like “Shani Louk Full Video” re-victimize affected people and lead users to dehumanising and disturbing content.</li>
  <li>TikTok uses victims and violence to drive engagement and, ultimately, revenue.</li>
  <li>Serious problems for users’ mental health could ensue, who can be (re-)traumatized by just clicking on the search suggestions.</li>
  <li>This poses a grave risk to public discourse by encouraging propagandists and <a href="https://fortune.com/2023/10/12/tiktok-paid-promoted-videos-platform-israel-palestine-hamas-misinformation/">free riders using paid ads to appear in the search results and aiming for engagement</a>.</li>
</ul>

<p>Once you click on one of those suggested search strings, you get redirected to a results page. Although the terms are in German (due to our sock puppet being logged in in Germany as a German account), the results shown are from around the world and span different languages. The videos one sees range from disturbing violent material to Imams talking about the end of the world to people praying for Israel. Most of those videos are provided without any context or explanations and will likely be hard to understand for many German users. Disturbingly enough for people of every age group, this also poses a special risk to TikTok’s relatively young user base, since Gen Z is known to use TikTok as a <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/09/16/technology/gen-z-tiktok-search-engine.html">search engine</a> and <a href="https://reutersinstitute.politics.ox.ac.uk/sites/default/files/2023-06/Digital_News_Report_2023.pdf">news source</a>.</p>

<p>So, while TikTok brags about not having political ads on the platform (which is not entirely true, as we have shown <a href="https://tiktok-audit.com/blog/2023/We-found-100-political-ads-on-TikTok-Germany/">here</a>), it drags users into one of the most violent, controversial and complicated political conflicts of our times by suggesting to search for these topics and not providing any context or help.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="suggested-search" /><category term="search," /><category term="war" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An analysis of the suggested searches related to the Israel-Hamas War]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">🔭 We found 100 political ads on TikTok Germany</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/We-found-100-political-ads-on-TikTok-Germany/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="🔭 We found 100 political ads on TikTok Germany" /><published>2023-09-25T12:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-09-25T12:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/We-found-100-political-ads-on-TikTok-Germany</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/We-found-100-political-ads-on-TikTok-Germany/"><![CDATA[<p><em>By: <a href="https://www.stiftung-nv.de/de/person/anna-semenova">Anna Semenova</a> and <a href="https://www.stiftung-nv.de/de/person/alexander-hohlfeld">Alexander Hohlfeld</a></em></p>

<p>In our blog post <a href="https://tiktok-audit.com/blog/2023/tiktok_political_ads/">Diving into TikTok’s Ad Library: Surfacing with Missing Data and Unenforced Guidelines</a> we found, that contrary to <a href="https://www.tiktok.com/creators/creator-portal/en-us/community-guidelines-and-safety/tiktoks-stance-on-political-ads/">TikTok´s guidelines</a> political advertising exists on the platform. Even though we argued that a systematic analysis is currently not possible, due to a lack of information provided by the ad library, we took a closer look at it and developed methods to assess the prevalence more in-depth. We matched names of politicians and political parties with the names of accounts that posted ads or those who paid for an ad.</p>

<p>But this is a very limited analysis and therefore our general criticism persists: TikTok needs to provide more features and data for the ad library to serve it’s purpose. For example, the videos are missing textual descriptions like hashtags the users would see. TikTok could also provide subtitles, that would allow researchers to automatically analyse what is said.</p>

<p>In the meantime, our limited approach offers a glimpse at the prevalence of political ads in specific contexts. But there is a major limitation: comparing politicians names with the available data only brings up those ads that are provided or paid for directly by political parties and candidates themselves. It is possible that political ads that are provided by third parties (e.g., lobby groups) could be even more prevalent, as they could be used to intentionally circumvent TikToks ban as well als political regulation on political ads.</p>

<p>Our analysis is based on the data of over <strong>7.5 million advertisements that included Germany as a target country over the period from 01.10.2022 to 31.08.2023</strong>.</p>

<p>As described above we queried our dataset with the names of politicians. We compiled a list of names of 1.) members of the the German parliament (MdBs), 2.) members of the German federal parliaments (MdLs) as well as 3.) all members of the European parliament (MEPs), searching for the personal names in the usernames and the ad sponsors. Additionally, we also looked for the party names in those data fields.</p>

<p>In total, we found 105 ads.</p>

<center>
<figure class="justify-content-sm-center">

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-09_tt_political_ads_by_accounts-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-09_tt_political_ads_by_accounts-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-09_tt_political_ads_by_accounts-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/2023-09_tt_political_ads_by_accounts.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

</figure>
</center>

<p>While the SPD posted the most ads in total, the majority is related to one campaign. If we look at the number of different accounts that used ads we can see that members of the AfD made the most attempts of posting political ads:</p>

<center>
<figure class="justify-content-sm-center">

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-09_tt_political_ads_by_party-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-09_tt_political_ads_by_party-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-09_tt_political_ads_by_party-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/2023-09_tt_political_ads_by_party.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

</figure>
</center>

<p>While most ads were not targeted at a specific audience, we also found that some political ads include particular targeting criteria. This is relevant to the current debate as microtargeting in political advertising has been scrutinised for a while and is part of an <a href="https://oeil.secure.europarl.europa.eu/oeil/popups/ficheprocedure.do?reference=2021/0381(COD)&amp;l=en">ongoing debate in the European Union</a>, with the European Data Protection Supervisor <a href="http://arguing/%20for%20tighter/">arguing for tighter</a> regulations. Specifically, we found, for example, that “News &amp; Information” was the main interest category targeted by political ads. Still, we also found ads targeting specific topics like the Bavarian FDP politician whose <a href="https://library.tiktok.com/ads/detail/?ad_id=1765779799994426">talk show monologue on early childhood education</a> was shown as an ad to 3000 German users interested in “Kids &amp; Maternity”; or AFD’s Frank Rinck <a href="https://library.tiktok.com/ads/detail/?ad_id=1755552014103605">4-minute ad of a speech in the Bundestag arguing for agricultural self-sufficiency</a> was shown to about 5000 users interested in “Appliances, Vehicles &amp; Transportation, Tech &amp; Electronics”.</p>

<center>
<figure class="justify-content-sm-center">

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-09_tt_political_ads_by_targeting-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-09_tt_political_ads_by_targeting-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/2023-09_tt_political_ads_by_targeting-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/2023-09_tt_political_ads_by_targeting.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

</figure>
</center>

<p>The whole set of political ads we found in the TikTok ad-library can be <a href="/assets/data/2023-09_political_ads.csv">downloaded as csv</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="ad-library" /><category term="ads," /><category term="analysis," /><category term="political-ads" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An update on political ads in Germany + Dataset]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">🔞 Ad-Targeting for minors still exists but it shouldn’t</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/ads-targeting-minors/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="🔞 Ad-Targeting for minors still exists but it shouldn’t" /><published>2023-08-28T20:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-08-28T20:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/ads-targeting-minors</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/ads-targeting-minors/"><![CDATA[<p><em>By: <a href="https://www.stiftung-nv.de/de/person/dr-martin-degeling">Martin Degeling</a> &amp; <a href="https://www.stiftung-nv.de/de/person/anna-semenova">Anna Semenova</a></em></p>

<p>Owner: Martin</p>

<p>On June 28th, TikTok <a href="https://www.tiktok.com/business/en/blog/privacy-updates-improved-data-control-transparency-tools">announced</a> that “Starting today […] people in the United States aged 13 to 15 will no longer see personalized ads on TikTok based on their activities off TikTok. From Tuesday, July 11, people in the European Economic Area, United Kingdom, and Switzerland aged 13 to 17 will no longer see personalized ads on TikTok based on their activities on or off TikTok”.</p>

<p>The changes in the EEA are related to the Digital Services Act coming into force - Article 28 (2) on “Online protection of minors” prohibits profiled advertisements for minors.</p>

<p>Now that TikTok has made its ads library publicly available, we wanted to test whether TikTok actually followed through on these announcements. And they do not. There are still ads targeted specifically to minors, and there is no barrier for advertisers to place these ads.</p>

<p>Here is how we come to that conclusion:</p>

<p>More than 7.000.000 ads in the ad library have been targeted at a German audience since October 2022. Most ads are not targeted at any specific age group, which means all age groups except 13-17 are listed. But over 3000 have been targeted only at minors (ages 13-17). And out of those, only 22 have been removed.</p>

<p>This is not surprising, in general. TikTok only announced an ending to this practice in July. Therefore, we expected to see a drop in the number of ads targeted at minors after July 11th. But this is not the case. The following histogram shows the number of ads targeted at minors per day over the whole time span. There is no indication that targeting minors has stopped or even declined since July 11th.</p>

<center>
<figure class="justify-content-sm-center">

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/tt_adtargeting_minors_histogram.svg-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/tt_adtargeting_minors_histogram.svg-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/tt_adtargeting_minors_histogram.svg-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/tt_adtargeting_minors_histogram.svg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

</figure>
</center>
<p><em>Histogram of the number of ads targeting only users 13-17 years old</em></p>

<p>While targeting only minors is not super common in Germany, the fact that it is still happening, although TikTok claimed to have disabled it, is surprising. See, for example, this <a href="https://library.tiktok.com/ads/detail/?ad_id=1773031834457089">Warner Brothers ad</a> for the movie Meg2. It is targeted at male users between 13-17 and the “audience” feature is set to “yes”. Enabling this feature means that ads are “<strong>based on the users’ on and off-TikTok activity as specified by the advertiser.”</strong> Activity-based targeting is explicitly mentioned in the TikTok press release as being deactivated by July 11th.</p>

<p>Out of curiosity, we wanted to see what changes TikTok had implemented to prevent this type of targeting on the platform. We used a business TikTok account to get quotes for promoting a video.</p>

<p>The screenshot below shows that TikTok implemented at least some kind of measure. When selecting 13-17 as your audience, the interface says <em>“Metrics cannot be displayed due to data security requirements for minors”.</em></p>

<div class="row justify-content-sm-center"><div class="col-sm-4 mt-3 mt-md-0">
<center>
<figure class="justify-content-sm-center">

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/tt_targeting_13-17_estimate-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/tt_targeting_13-17_estimate-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/tt_targeting_13-17_estimate-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/tt_targeting_13-17_estimate.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

</figure>
</center>
</div></div>
<p><em>Screenshot from the TikTok App not-showing estimates for the audience size for 13-17 yo</em></p>

<p>However, this limited data disclosure has only been implemented for the estimated audience. After specifying the targeting criteria for an ad, we are asked to specify the budget and duration of the ad placement. In that process (as seen in the screenshot below) TikTok discloses our ads’ “Estimated video views”. While TikTok does not disclose the exact audience size of 13-17-year-olds in Germany who are interested in Education, we now see a lower bound for the same target group and learn that about 266.519 to 709.520 users in that audience are expected to be online within a day.</p>

<div class="row justify-content-sm-center"><div class="col-sm-4 mt-3 mt-md-0">
<center>
<figure class="justify-content-sm-center">

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/tt_targeting_13-17_education_estimate-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/tt_targeting_13-17_education_estimate-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/tt_targeting_13-17_education_estimate-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/tt_targeting_13-17_education_estimate.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

</figure>
</center>
</div></div>
<p><em>Screenshot from the TikTok App showing estimated views from the target group</em></p>

<p>The fact that targeting minors with ads targeting not only their age, but also gender and interests, which TikTok infers from user behaviour, is not only in violation with TikTok’s own announcement but also the Digital Services Act that prohibits this type of advertising.</p>

<p>PS: Here is a list of the advertisers that target minors most often:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Warner Bros. Entertainment GmbH                          283
Non-trivial                                               93
eBay Kleinanzeigen GmbH                                   63
Bayerischer Jugendring                                    62
Scoolio GmbH                                              60
GHIS School                                               59
www.bpods.de                                              53
ethno IQ GmbH                                             52
EF Educational Foundation for Foreign Study AG            45
Ministerium der Justiz des Landes Nordrhein-Westfalen     45
FRØSLEV AFTERSCHOOL                                       39
LEONINE Distribution GmbH                                 36
Handelsverband Deutschland - HDE e.V.                     35
Pikoya Ltd.                                               34
HuLab GmbH                                                31
Scopely, Inc.                                             30
epods1                                                    29
neo venture GmbH                                          29
lukas.pain                                                28
Party Club Berlin Freizeitkultugestaltung e.V.            28
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="ad-library" /><category term="ads," /><category term="analysis" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An data analysis of ads targeting minors on a set of 7.000.000 ads shows that, altough TikTok claimed it ended the practice, still exists]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">🤿 Diving into TikTok’s Ad Library: Surfacing with Missing Data and Unenforced Guidelines</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/tiktok_political_ads/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="🤿 Diving into TikTok’s Ad Library: Surfacing with Missing Data and Unenforced Guidelines" /><published>2023-08-18T11:20:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-08-18T11:20:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/tiktok_political_ads</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/tiktok_political_ads/"><![CDATA[<p><em>By: <a href="https://www.stiftung-nv.de/de/person/alexander-hohlfeld">Alexander Hohlfeld</a></em></p>

<p>In April 2020 TikTok announced their new “<a href="https://newsroom.tiktok.com/de-de/richtlinien-fur-werbeanzeigen-auf-tiktok">Guidelines for advertisements on TikTok</a>”, which explicitly forbid political advertisements on the platform. TikTok claimed that they “will not allow paid ads that explicitly promote or oppose political candidates, officeholders, political parties, or groups or issues at the federal, state, or local levels”. An <a href="https://foundation.mozilla.org/en/campaigns/tiktok-political-ads/">investigation</a> by Mozilla in 2021 already had shown that the political ad policies can easily be circumvented with influencer marketing. Therefore, TikTok <a href="https://newsroom.tiktok.com/de-de/aktualisierung-der-richtlinien-fuer-politische-accounts">updated</a> these guidelines and introduced a “comprehensive monetization block for political accounts”.</p>

<p>Until recently it wasn’t possible to systematically prove whether and how strongly TikTok enforced all these guidelines. With the Digital Services Act (DSA) putting more pressure on transparency efforts of “Very Large Online Platforms” (VLOPs), TikTok introduced their “<a href="https://newsroom.tiktok.com/en-eu/expanding-tiktoks-research-api-and-commercial-content-library">Commercial Content Library</a>” in July 2023.</p>

<p>In the corresponding <a href="https://library.tiktok.com/faq">FAQ</a> they point out, that “TikTok does not show political or election ads on the platform. <strong>So you will not be able to find ads of political nature in the Commercial Content Library</strong>”. But surprisingly, it is not complicated at all to find such ads. Even though the library lacks important information, the way how easy it is to find political advertising raises questions on how seriously TikTok enforces these guidelines. A simple <a href="https://twitter.com/favstats/status/1681991000623816705">search for the abbreviations</a> of German political parties already shows numerous examples of ads placed by politicians or parties as well as a seemingly endless number of political ads by other people. Especially politicians of the “AfD” seem to use ads on TikTok systematically to reach out to potential voters. We found examples of accounts from members of the German parliament (MdBs) and members from the federal parliaments (MdLs). Besides that, we found even more political ads promoting the AfD, that are not associated with an official account of a member of the party. Even though other parties don’t seem to use TikTok ads to a similar extent, we also found examples of accounts of city and local chapters of political parties advertising political content.</p>

<center>
<figure class="justify-content-sm-center">

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/tt_adlib_afd-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/tt_adlib_afd-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/tt_adlib_afd-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/tt_adlib_afd.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

</figure>
</center>
<center>
<figure class="justify-content-sm-center">

  <picture>
    
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/tt_adlib_spd_ffm-480.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/tt_adlib_spd_ffm-800.webp" />
    <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/tt_adlib_spd_ffm-1400.webp" />
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/tt_adlib_spd_ffm.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

</figure>
</center>
<p><em>Screenshots from the search results for different political parties</em></p>

<p>There are many indications that the German context is no coincidence and the political ad policies are not strongly enforced in other contexts as well. Journalists of the <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/iainmartin/2023/07/26/tiktok-chinese-propaganda-ads-europe/">Forbes</a> magazine revealed even that “TikTok has pushed Chinese propaganda ads to millions across Europe”.</p>

<p>The TikTok ad library can be seen as a starting point, enforcing transparency and data access obligations under the DSA. For a more systematic analysis the library lacks important information. TikTok also deleted some ads due to violations of their terms of service (“You can’t view this ad because it was removed from the platform due to a violation of TikTok’s terms.”). While it is possible to get the information that a specific ad was removed, neither the ad itself nor any information about the advertiser is shown on the library, making it impossible to draw any conclusions from it.</p>

<p>Auditing the specific flaws or bias of TikTok´s advertising system would require that information and also more detailed search options than just the search for advertiser name and keyword. The descriptions of ads are also not disclosed in TikTok’s ad library, making it very difficult to find the exact product or service the ad is referring to.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, it was very easy to find anecdotal evidence from TikTok´s ad library, to show that there is a lack of enforcement on the political advertising guidelines. A systematic analysis is currently not possible due to lack of information provided by the library. We hope, that TikTok adjusts the functionality and provides more information, so that researchers can use the ad library to conduct systematic research.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="ad-library" /><category term="ads," /><category term="analysis," /><category term="political-ads" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A short analysis of political ads and TikToks new advertisement library]]></summary></entry></feed>